<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian curtesie: or, St. Pauls vltimum vale Deliuered in two sermons, on 2. Cor. 13.11. at St. Margarets on Fish-street-hill in London. By N. Rogers (sometimes preacher there) at his farewel, vpon his remoueal thence to a pastoral charge else-where.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Nehemiah, 1593-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1152:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian curtesie: or, St. Pauls vltimum vale Deliuered in two sermons, on 2. Cor. 13.11. at St. Margarets on Fish-street-hill in London. By N. Rogers (sometimes preacher there) at his farewel, vpon his remoueal thence to a pastoral charge else-where.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Nehemiah, 1593-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 77, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for Edward Brewster: and are to bee sould at his shop, at the west end of Pauls, at the signe of the Star,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Curteſie: <hi>OR,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAVLS <hi>Vltimum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deliuered in two Sermons, on 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. <hi>at</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARGARETS <hi>on</hi> Fiſh-ſtreet-hill in London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> N. ROGERS (<hi>ſometimes Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> there) at his Farewel, vpon his remoueal thence to a Paſtoral charge elſe-where.</p>
            <q>As many as walk according to this rule, peace ſhall be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and mercy, and vpon the Iſrael of God. <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewſter:</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhop, at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> at the Signe of the Bear, 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT Vertuous, and truely Religious Lady, the Lady</hi> Margaret Chiborne (<hi>late wife to that worthy, and Worſhipfull</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, Sir <hi>Charles Chiborne,</hi> Serieant at the Lawe, deceaſed) long life and good daies, with increaſe of Grace here, and eternall Glorie hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GOOD MADAME:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was no ſooner purpoſed to let this Copie paſſe the Preſſe, but I was as ſoone reſolued to ſend it foorth vnder ſhelter of your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips name, prefixed on the front. I knowe, Gods word can countenance it ſelfe, and needes no ſhelter of any humane arme: Yet I finde, not onely the writings of the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:16595:3"/>
and beſt; but euen ſome of thoſe holy books in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired from Heauen, bearing in their fore-heads (as from the pen-men) a dedication. To your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips name I then inſcribe this; theſe reaſons e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially mee thereunto inducing:</p>
            <p>Firſt, your Ladiſhip had a ſpeciall hand in the firſt being &amp; birth of it: for, it was by your means and furtherance, that I was remooued from the place where then I was, to that where now I am: vpon which occaſion, theſe Sermons were there preached. Which great loue and vndeſerued fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour cauſed mee a good while ſince to regiſter in my heart a grateful acknowledgement: and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting means in real requitance to expreſs the ſame, I haue now preſum'd in this dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of your own worth: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of if I ſhould make a due report, they which know you not, would judge I flatter; and if leſſe, the which knowe you and your affection towards me, would ſay, I were vnthankfull. This I will onely ſay, That whereas the moſt of your place and rank,<note place="margin">Luke 10.40. Verſe 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> like <hi>Martha,</hi> incumber themſelues about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny needleſſe things; you, like <hi>Mary,</hi> haue choſen the better part. Your loue to GOD, zeal to his houſe, teſtified by your frequent repairing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, your daily performane of religious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; yea, priuately in your cloſet were God onely ſeeth and regardeth: your conuerſation lead <hi>in fear</hi> (the fruit of all the former) teſtifie of you,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.17</note> as did the piety &amp; godlineſſe of that Lady to whom that bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote,<note place="margin">3 Iohn 11</note> that you are <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16595:3"/>
whereof you haue more cauſe to boaſt, then of any outward honour whatſoeuer. For, what is greatneſſe without goodneſſe? but like the Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans nightingale, a meer ſound and nothing elſe. Go on, good Madam, in your godly courſe: and whiles others ſtriue to ſettle their lands, ſecure their monies, confirm their eſtates (leauing their ſaluation vnwrought vp) let it be your principal endeauour, To conform your life ſtill more and more to the rule of Gods moſt holy word, and to make ſure your election vnto your ſelf. For,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10</note> when men haue beat their brains, broke their ſleep, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their marrow, to bee wealthy, mighty; yet at laſt they ſhall be enforced to confeſſe, that To be ſaued was ſimply the beſt plot. Neither will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtudy yeeld true ſolid comfort, but what was ſpent about it.</p>
            <p>Let not this my preſumption bee offenſiue to your Ladiſhip. It is more I owe vnto you than I can perform. Let my confeſſion teſtifie my obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gednes; and this bee a witnes of my thankfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of my duety: wherein I deſire to pleaſe at leaſt God, not to offend at leaſt you. The Lord make you to encreaſe and abound yet more and more in grace and goodnes,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.12.13</note> and make your hart ſtable and vnblameable in all holineſs againſt the coming of our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. And ſo I reſt; and ſtill will reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Petitioner to the Lord for your Ladiſhips beſt welfare, NEHEMIAH ROGERS.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Meſsing in Eſſex.</hi> 
                  <date>Aug. 1. 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16595:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader; eſpecially, to his louing <hi>Friends and late auditours, the</hi> Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners of S. <hi>Margarets</hi> Fiſh-ſtreet, with all <hi>truely-Religious in or about</hi> London <hi>by</hi> whoſe fauour or bounty my Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>there hath been countenanced or</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way furthered: all bleſſings which earth affords, or <hi>heauen contains, be</hi> multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a good husbandman deals with his plants; pruning ſome, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing others, for their better growth: ſo dealeth that most wiſe and carefull husbandman of the Church,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.1</note> with the members of it. Some <hi>hee purgeth,</hi> that they may growe more fruitfull: Others <hi>hee takes away,</hi> that are not fruitfull. Oftentimes he
<pb facs="tcp:16595:5"/>
tranſlateth others from off that ſoil whereon they grewe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.9</note> and plants them on ſom other grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; and that either becauſe of the barrenneſs of the ſoyl, or vnfruitfulnes of the plant, or for ſome other cauſe beſt known vnto himſelfe. It hath pleaſed him in mercie not to ſupplant, as iuſtly hee might haue done, and that for euer, but onely to remoue me into another corner of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard (Bleſſed bee his name it is any where within that pale). The ſoyle wheron I grewe, was fat and goodly (neuer plant could growe on better) no fault in it, of this tranſlation. The Plant it ſelf was badde and barren: and that (as ſafeſt it is for me to iudge) occaſions it. I haue but loytered, when I ſhould haue laboured, in gods harueſt. Now Lord forgiue it mee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.24</note>Seeing now I muſt leaue you, <hi>my loue my Brethren I leaue with you;</hi> and this as a teſtimonie of my loue. When I am out of ſight I would not bee forgotten. Read and practiſe what here you finde, and what formerly you haue beard: and I dare ſay I ſhall not bee. Theſe are the last Sermons that I preached amongst you: let them not bee leaſt eſteemed: take them as the laſt Farewell of a hearty friend. When they were preached to the eare, paſſion hindered many of your attentions: I now preſent them to your eye,<note place="margin">Luke 1.4</note> that you may bee more fully enformed of thoſe things wherein you were then inſtructed.</p>
            <p>Let it ſuffice, my Affection is ſo great towards you, that I cannot expreſs it. God workes my heart to loue thoſe that loue him. The Lord imprint in your minds this ſeale of that my Affection vnfeyned, and enable you by his grace to doe his will;<note place="margin">Acts 20.32.</note> that ſo at laſt you may bee made partakers of a glorious inheritance amongſt all them which are ſanctified: which ſhall be faithfully prayed, for by him</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>That vnfainedly deſires your ſaluation, <hi>NEHEMIAH ROGERS.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Meſſing.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 1. 1621.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16595:5"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Curteſie, <hi>OR,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVLS <hi>Vltimum Vale.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. COR. 13.11.</hi>
                  </bibl> Finally, Brethren, Farewell: Bee perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr bleſſed Apoſtle, Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> hauing in this Epiſtle purged himſelfe from ſuch crimes as he was charged withal, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine falſe teachers, who were crept into the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth;</hi> and eſpecially from that which was the ground of all,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.5.</note> his not comming amongſt them according vnto promiſe made (for which they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16595:6"/>
accuſed him of leuity and inconſtancy) doth in the beginning of this Chapter renew his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note place="margin">The order of the words.</note> telling them of his readineſſe a third time to come amongſt them, and withall ſheweth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what manner it ſhall be; namely, with ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and more then wonted rigour, againſt ſuch as were obſtinate. Now being to make an end, he windes vp all with a friendly Farewel, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he doth ſomewhat allay and mitigate what-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he had formerly wrot that might ſauour of bitterneſſe: and that hee might not leaue their minds exaſperated, hee giues them a taſte of the louing affection hee bare towards them, in this his valediction. <hi>Finally, Brethren, Farewell:</hi> which words,<note place="margin">The ſumme of them.</note> with the other following in the verſes ſubſequent, containe in them the concluſion of the whole Epiſtle, which is ſpent in <hi>Exhortation, Salutation,</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi> The <hi>Exhortation</hi> is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this 11. verſe. The <hi>Salutation,</hi> verſe 12, 13. The <hi>Prayer</hi> verſe 14.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The logicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</note>In this Exhortation we may conſider, Firſt the <hi>Manner</hi> of it. <hi>Finally, Brethren, Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly the <hi>Matter</hi> of it; <hi>Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Manner,</hi> we haue, Firſt, a <hi>note of conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Finally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a <hi>Louing compellation: Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, a <hi>Friendly valediction: Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Matter,</hi> obſerue wee, Firſt the <hi>duties</hi> whereto exhorted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16595:6"/>Secondly, the <hi>motiue</hi> or <hi>argument</hi> wherewith they are enforced.</p>
            <p>The <hi>duties,</hi> foure; Firſt <hi>Perfection; Be perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>mutuall conſolation; Bee of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>vnanimity</hi> or <hi>conſent</hi> in matters eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall. <hi>Be of one minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>concord</hi> and <hi>agreement</hi> in matter do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall and ciuill: <hi>Liue in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Argument taken, <hi>à Commodo,</hi> from the profit that thereby will inſue: <hi>The God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The interpretations of theſe words be vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: we will ſearch for the beſt.<note place="margin">The Theologicall expoſition.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally.</hi> Some read it thus; <hi>For the reſt;</hi> others,<note place="margin">Text. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>For the Remainder:</hi> Not much amiſſe to take either. For ſo the word here vſed ſignifieth, and may haue reference either to the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> or to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> To the Apoſtle thus; as if hee had ſayd, <hi>I haue written as large vnto you, yet ſtill there is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder behind for me to exhort you vnto, which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in theſe few words: Be perfect: Be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, &amp;c.</hi> To the people thus; As if he had ſayd, <hi>Hitherto I haue not been wanting in my dutie, but haue ſufficiently inſtructed and admoniſhed you, &amp;c. Now the remainder is for you, that you doe your dutie and obey my precepts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> There bee three ſorts of Brethren mentioned in holy Scripture: Firſt, ſuch as are brethren by <hi>Race:</hi> as they who haue the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> had;<note place="margin">Gen. 25.25.</note> or they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16595:7"/>
who are of the ſame ſtock and kinred:<note place="margin">Gen. 13.8</note> and ſo <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> were called Brethren.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch as are Brethren by <hi>Place,</hi> who are of the ſame nation and countrey: and ſo the <hi>Iewes</hi> are tearmed Brethren in the Law;<note place="margin">Deut. 23.20</note> 
               <hi>To a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thou maist lend vpon vſury, but not vnto thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuch as are Brethren by <hi>Grace;</hi> and that either more <hi>common,</hi> or more <hi>ſpeciall.</hi> More com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in reſpect of <hi>creation,</hi> and ſo all men are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:<note place="margin">Gen. 9.5</note> 
               <hi>At the hand of a mans brother will I require the life of man;</hi> more ſpeciall in reſpect of <hi>Adoption,</hi> and ſo Chriſtians are Brethren, and they onely. In this reſpect doth the Apoſtle call them Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi> The word ſignifieth properly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and is by moſt ſo tranſlated and read. Yet <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and ſome others, renders it as wee haue it, as well he may: for, the word ſignifieth as wel <hi>Farewell</hi> as <hi>Reioyce:</hi> wherein the Apoſtle wiſheth all good to betide them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Be perfect.</hi> The ſignification of this verbe is likewiſe diuerſe, and by ſom rendred for conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; by others, for reſtauration. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's meaning is, that whereas the members of this Church were all as it were bones diſplaced and out of joynt, they ſhould now again bee joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in loue, and they ſhould endeauour to make perfect what was amiſſe amongſt them, either in faith or manners: They ſhould bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in reſpect of truth, though not is reſpect of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16595:7"/>
abſoluteneſs; they ſhould deſire and endeauour after perfection, though in act they attain it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be of good comfort,</hi> or take yee comfort.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Some read it thus, <hi>Take exhortation:</hi> for, the word heer vſed ſignifieth indifferently, to <hi>comfort,</hi> to <hi>exhort,</hi> to <hi>intreat</hi> But the former reading is beſt liked by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who thinketh the Apoſtle rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends conſolation than exhortation, in regard of the many oppoſitions and trials they had &amp; were to meet withall in their courſe of Chriſtianity; and therfore willes them to chear vp themſelues, and mutually one another, that they may not make ſhipwrack of their faith in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bee of one minde;</hi> to wit, in matters of faith and religion. For, by this precept he ſeemeth to note out, that ſome things were amiſſe amongſt them, and that many things were done through conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vain-glory: Hee wills them therefore to be alike-minded and affectioned, that all diſcord and diſſenſion might be auoided, and the Church no way thereby troubled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liue in Peace.</hi> Peace is of three ſorts: <hi>Eternall,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is cald <hi>Pax Numinis,</hi> the peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, which wee haue with him through Chriſt; <hi>Internall,</hi> which is called <hi>Pax pectoris,</hi> the peace of conſcience, which is a fruit of the former, and proceeds from that; <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall,</hi> which is called <hi>Pax temporis,</hi> the peace w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> wee haue with men for the time wee liue in the world. This laſt onely is heer meant: and this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16595:8"/>
precept reſpects things ciuil, as the former things eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <q>And the God of loue and peace ſhall bee with you.</q>
            <p>Som conſtrue this clauſe by way of enunciation affirmatiuely; as if the Apoſtle ſhould haue ſaid, In thus doing you ſhall haue the bleſſing of God attending you, &amp;c: Others Imprecatory, by way of wiſh or praier; as if hee had ſaid, The God of loue and peace be with you, and enable you to do thus. But the former is the better.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God of loue and peace.</hi> Hee is ſo tearmed, firſt (ſay ſome) becauſe he is loue and peace it ſelf, it is his Eſſence; ſecondly, becauſe he delights and takes pleaſure in it; and thirdly and eſpecially, becauſe hee is the Authour and Giuer of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall be with you.</hi> That is, by his gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and comfortable preſence, to bleſſe you and defend you.</p>
            <p>Thus then we ſee the meaning, as if the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſhould haue in larger manner thus ſaid:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe.</note>
               <hi>Hitherto I haue at large written vnto you, O yee Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, whom I tenderly affect euen as my Brethren in Chriſt, and to whom I wiſh all welfare and happineſs both in the things of this life and of a better: And yet ther is a remainder, and ſomething left to bee done, which (that I may conclude) in brief is this; That you endeuor to perfection, purging out ſin, increaſing in grace, and ſo making vp what is amongst you wanting; As alſo that you mutually comfort one the other, and take comfort one of another, that you may the better bee enabled to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the many oppoſitions you are like to meet withall in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16595:8"/>
the courſe of Chriſtianity. See alſo that you be alike min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and affected in matters of religion, that the Church may not bee troubled by your diuiſions and diſſenſions. And, in things ciuill, let there be a like concord and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment found amongſt you, as betweene neighbour and neighbour, husband and wife, parent and childe, maister and ſeruant, and the like: which if there be, then that God who takes delight in loue and peace, and who is the rewarder of them that liue in loue and peace, and who is the Author and Donor of theſe graces of loue &amp; peace, ſhall be with you by his gracious protection and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table preſence, and ſhall bleſſe you, and beſtowe vpon you all good bleſsings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we haue ſeen the Apoſtles meaning. Now wee come to ſpeak of ſome ſuch profitable inſtructions as theſe words ſhall afford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally.</hi> The Apoſtle, as we ſee,<note place="margin">Text.</note> had written largely to theſe Corinthians, and yet there is ſtill a remainder behinde: for ſo the word ſignifieth (as wee haue before ſeene). Hence then wee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though Gods Miniſters ſpend their time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Miniſters haue euer ſomething left to do after their greateſt pains. <hi>1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and take the greatest pains that can bee taken, in teaching and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting their people; yet there will bee ſtill a Remainder, and ſomething left to bee done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not without cauſe and reaſon then is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters task and toil paralleled with the <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who hath no vacation: the end of one work is but the beginning of another: euery ſeaſon of the yeer bringeth his ſeuerall trauell with it. So that no calling is accompanied with more labour<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16595:9"/>
or leſſe eaſe.<note place="margin">Ier. 4.3</note> And thus the <hi>Miniſter:</hi> Hath hee broke vp the fallow ground of his peoples harts? then muſt he ſowe the precious ſeed therin.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6</note> Hath he ſowed ſeed? then muſt he water what he hath ſet and ſowed.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.25</note> Yea, tares and weeds will growe and ſoon ſprout vp, ſleep we neuer ſo little; and therefore great need of daily weeding.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let this then ſtoppe the mouths of ſuch as cry out againſt the Miniſter for an idle calling, and account Miniſters of all others to liue the eaſieſt liues, as hauing leaſt to doo of any. I confeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as ſome vſe it, it is a calling of exceſſiue idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.1</note> when they feed themſelues, but not the flock; and doo not gather, but eat the hony. Of ſuch it may be ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.28</note> as our Sauiour of the Lillies in the field, <hi>They labour not.</hi> But, conſider it in its owne nature, and as it ought to bee performed, wee ſhall finde it to bee a ſeruice of great imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his task to be an endleſſe task: ſo that none can haue juſt cauſe to ſay, that, becauſe he is a Miniſter, he hath an eaſie occupation &amp; calling to follow. Harueſt-labourers of all other are the ſoreſt labourers, as wee knowe; no labour more toilſome than theirs is: that, of all others, as wee ſay,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.37</note> is the ſore-ſweating labour. And are not Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſuch? ſurely the ſweat of the Miniſtry (be it followed as it ought) exceeds the ſweat of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther callings, and with the ſoreſt labourer doth the painfull Miniſter eat his bread in the ſweat of his brows. There is a labour of the ſoule as well as of the body; as there is a ſuffering of the ſoule
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16595:9"/>
as well as a ſuffering of the body. And look as the ſuffering of the ſoule exceeds by farre any paines that the body vndergoeth (for,<note place="margin">Pro. 18.14</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit of a man will ſustain his infirmity</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) but a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit who can bear?</hi>); ſo doth the ſoule-labour exceed any other labour whatſoeuer. Say not then, that Miniſters are idle, and their callings ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, becauſe they labour not with their hands. What though a Gouerner of a ſhip ſitteth ſtill at the ſtern, while ſome climb the maſt, and others walk vpon the hatches, and others labour at the pump? for, though he doth not as they doo, yet he doth far greater and better things. Their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling then is not eaſie, idle;<note place="margin">It is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a painfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, humeris angelorum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midandum.</note> but laborious and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: as it is an honour, ſo it is a burden, and ſuch a one as requireth the ſtrength of Angels.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this taxeth ſuch as, being entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſame calling and function of the Miniſtry,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> liue an idle life, and ſit them down to reſt, &amp; with <hi>Iſachar</hi> think eaſe is good,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.14</note> eſpecially if they haue for ſome times heertofore laboured in the word and doctrine. Such little vnderſtand the nature of their office, as hauing laid ſome grounds of knowledge, neglect the daily vrging of practice and perſeuerance. A great part of the building is behinde, after the foundation is laid. Theſe are they that occaſion the world to judge of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Cretians,</hi> to be <hi>ſlowe-bellies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit 1.12</note> I take no pleaſure in defiling my owne neaſt, nor in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open the nakednes of men of my owne coat: But God forbid that I ſhould as a Fly lie blowing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16595:10"/>
vpon their ſores, or vſe my tongue to licke their filthy vlcers. Let ſuch bee what they will, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther idle or vnable, like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Hen too fat to lay; they are a burden to our Church, a diſgrace vnto our calling, which allows vs no time of ſitting ſtil. <hi>Why ſtand you heer all the day idle?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.6</note> It was the Lord of the Vineyards reproof to them that ſtood idle but in the market-place: what ſharpneſſe then muſt ſuch look for as ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not in the market-place but in the Vineyard, and idle too; and all their day? It is ill being idle in the market, but much worſe to ſtand idle in the Vineyard of the Lord. Let vs then,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.1</note> ſo many as haue receiued this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.13</note> not faint; <hi>but giue attendance to reading, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, to doctrine.</hi> Is knowledge planted? then practice muſt bee vrged. Is their practice good? then perſeuerance, progreſſe and continuance, muſt bee preſſed. A Souldier ſhould dy in the wars ſtanding, and a Miniſter in the pulpit prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; no better place to haue God finde vs in. And, when thou ſtandeſt idle, admoniſh thy ſelfe as ſometimes <hi>Plinius Secundus</hi> admoniſhed his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew;<note place="margin">Poteras has ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras non perdere Plin Secund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in Epiſt. ad Marci<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> Thou might'ſt haue not loſt theſe houres.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, let hearers hence learn their leſſon: for, is it ſo that though Gods Miniſters take the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> greateſt pains that can be taken, there will be ſtill ſomething left for them to doo? then certainely there is a remainder for you as well as they. Doſt thou know ſomthing? yet alas, how many things art thou ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of that thou art bound to know, and remaine for thee to learn! And though thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16595:10"/>
haſt knowledge in aboundance, ſo that thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with <hi>Salomon</hi> to diſcourſe from the <hi>Cedar-tree that is in Lebanon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 4.33.</note> 
               <hi>euen vnto the hyſope that ſpringeth out of the wall, and of all beaſts and fowls, fiſhes &amp; cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping things;</hi> yet ſtill there is a remainder, namely practice and obedience: for,<note place="margin">Iohn 13.17</note> 
               <hi>if you knowe theſe things, bleſſed are you if you doe them,</hi> ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>Think of theſe things, thou who art ſo puffed vp with a conceit of that ſame ſmall ſcantling of knowledge thou haſt receiued, as that thou neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecteſt all further means of edification. And doo thou alſo think of this, who conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tſt thy ſelf with a bare hearing of the word, without conſequent meditation or practice. Sermon is don, thou ſaiſt, when the Miniſter hath done preaching: and ſo it is indeed with many, for it is no more thought of after. But, the Sermon that wants conſequent meditation heere, may bee meditated of in hell heerafter. Remember that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> The Obſeruations from this <hi>Compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> are from the conſideration of <hi>Paul</hi> as a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or as an Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>If we conſider him thus calling them as he was a Chriſtian, then we obſerue,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a ſpirituall kinred and brotherhood amongst Christians.</hi> Such as profeſſe the ſame faith,<note place="margin">Doct. Chriſtians are ſpiritually a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> and worſhip the ſame God, are Brethren. And ſo we finde them often ſtiled in Scripture.<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.22.12</note> 
               <hi>I will declare thy Name vnto my Brethren</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) in the midſt of the congregation will I praiſe thee.</hi> And elſewhere
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16595:11"/>
thus;<note place="margin">Pſal. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.9 1 Cor. 5.11</note> 
               <hi>For my brethren and companions ſake, I will wiſh thee now proſperity.</hi> So the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth, <hi>If any that is called a Brother bee a fornicatour or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, &amp;c. with ſuch a one, no not to eat.</hi> And againe, <hi>The Brethren which are with mee vnto the Churches of Galatia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2</note> This our Sauiour ſheweth to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Mat. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8</note> when he ſaith, <hi>One is your Master, euen Christ; and all ye are Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Iames 1.18 Gal. 4.26 1 Pet. 1.23 1 cor. 10.16.17 2 Tim. 4.8</note>And no maruell: for, they haue one and the ſame <hi>Father,</hi> which is <hi>God;</hi> one and the ſame <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> which is the <hi>Church,</hi> in whoſe womb they lie together: they are begotten of the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>ſeed,</hi> which is the <hi>word:</hi> they are fed at one and the ſame table with the ſame <hi>nouriſhment;</hi> and look for one and the ſame <hi>inheritance,</hi> euen eternal <hi>happineſs</hi> and <hi>bleſſednes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let this ſerue, then, firſt for the <hi>Reproof</hi> of ſuch as diſdain to call Chriſtians by the name of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> or to giue any Saint ſuch a title, eſpecially if hee bee a mean one and of lowe rank. But, what diſparagement is it, or can it bee to any, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them to bee their Brethren whom Chriſt acknowledgeth to bee his Brethren, and God acknowledgeth to be his Sons? <hi>Foraſmuch as you haue done it to the leaſt of theſe my Brethren</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>you haue done it vnto me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.40. Heb. 2.11</note> Shall we be aſhamed of ſuch as Chriſt is not aſham'd of? Let vs beware of this pride of heart, which doth ſo puffe vs vp in regard of outward condition in the world, as that it maketh vs to forget ſuch as are mean and lowe; and cauſeth vs ſo to carry our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16595:11"/>
ſelues as if they were not our Brethren, of the ſame chriſtian calling &amp; profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with our ſelues. True it is, we are differenced in ciuill policy, and ciuill ſocieties; ſome being noble, ſome baſe; ſom rich, ſome poor (which differences, <hi>Religion</hi> doth not take away, nor aboliſh before men) yet in that ſpirituall ſociety, of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Chriſt is the Head, there is no ſuch diſtinction. Heer we are all one; all equals; all Brethren. Let not then our <hi>inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> in our ciuill calling cauſe great men to forget their <hi>equality</hi> in the Chriſtian; nor our <hi>equality</hi> in our Chriſtian, cauſe mean men to forget their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality</hi> in the ciuill. In both let vs carry our ſelues like men of wiſdome.</p>
            <p>And if theſe are to bee reproued, then much more are ſuch profane perſons to be ſoundly leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, who caſt this name of <hi>Brother</hi> as a word of reproach &amp; diſgrace vpon ſuch as fear the Lord: <hi>Oh, you are one of the holy Brethren, you are one of the holy Siſters.</hi> Now, what doo ſuch miſcreants, but through their ſides ſtrike the Prophets, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, yea and Chriſt himſelfe? Let ſuch knowe, that they openly proclaim as it were with a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, that they haue not God for their Father, nor the Church for their Mother; but do openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them from being their parents, while they profeſſe, that they are none of that holy Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <p>As this ſerueth for <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi> ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> place it may ſerue for our <hi>Inſtruction:</hi> for, out of this name wee may ſpell our duties. Look
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16595:12"/>
what nature ties natural Brethren vnto, that doth grace much more tie ſpirituall vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Duties of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note>
               <hi>Brethren</hi> (as we knowe) loue together, and liue peaceably one with another. There is vnity and amity amongſt them:<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> yea, ſo ſtrong is that loue which is amongſt Brethren, as that it exceeds all other loue amongſt men. It exceeds the loue in mariage (ſaith one) becauſe that is by choice, this by nature. It exceeds the loue betweene Parents and children, becauſe that is not reciprocall, for the inequality of the perſons: this is moſt equall. And therefore the Arabians and Weſt-Indians, as Hiſtories make mention, prefer brethren before children in inheritances. This is the loue of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by nature. Now, we haue obtained a more excellent Brotherhood, and therefore ought to loue; and loue as earneſtly. Our loue muſt be as the loue of Brethren: and ſo we are commanded, <hi>Be affectioned to loue one another with Brotherly loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.10 Heb. 13.1 2 Pet. 1.7</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. And againe, <hi>Let Brotherly loue continue.</hi> And againe, <hi>To godlineſſe adde Brotherly kindnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. in Apol. c. <hi>39.</hi> ad ſtupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Gentil.</note>In <hi>Tertullian</hi> his time, there was ſuch vnity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, and their loue each to other was ſo great, as that it was to the amazement of the Heathen. See, ſay they, how theſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans loue one another, and are ready to dy one for another. But alas for vs! our contentions and wranglings euen about toies and trifles may make men amazed. How ſhall God bee our Father, if we liue not together as louing brethren? Or how
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16595:12"/>
ſhall hee call vs his children, if wee behaue our ſelues as ſtrangers or enemies one vnto another? <hi>As touching Brotherly loue,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.9</note> 
               <hi>you need not that I write vnto you; for, you your ſelues are taught of God to loue one another:</hi> As if hee had ſaid, Look, as naturall Brethren, not degenerating nor growing out of kind, are taught by nature to loue one another; ſo you, to whom God hath giuen his holy Spirit, are taught by the ſame Spirit to liue in loue. If loue and amity bee a leſſon taught of God, then reaſon thus with thy ſelfe; <hi>Who tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth me to carry malice and hatred in my breaſt? who fils my mouth with railings &amp; curſed ſpeakings?</hi> O that wee would but think of this, and remember that wee are Brethren! then would there not bee ſo much bitterneſſe as there is, nor ſo much enuie, malice, ſpite, found among vs: for, a cauſe why theſe euills remain with vs, is, in that wee forget that we are Brethren. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.8</note> ſaid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to <hi>Lot, betwixt thee and mee, for wee are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> The very name of a Brother is, or I am ſure ought to bee, potent enough to quench coales of contention.</p>
            <p>Again: Brethren will take one anothers part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt enemies, though happely they may diſſent amongſt themſelues; ſo that wrong one, wrong all. Thus, <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes took the abuſe offred to their ſiſter, as if it had been offred vnto them; and thought it a ſufficient excuſe for them joining to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the reuenge of the Sichemites,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.31</note> in that it was done in their ſiſters quarrell: <hi>Should they abuſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16595:13"/>
our ſiſter as a whore?</hi> Thus ſhould Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend one another in lawfull courſes (I ſay not, in vnlawfull), and ſtep out for them when they are ſlandered and ſpoke euill of, and not then bee ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; as the maner of too-too many is, who flinch away as <hi>Demas</hi> and others did from <hi>Paul,</hi> leauing him to anſwer for himſelf. Thus, Brethren haue almoſt forgotten that they are Brethren; and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſtands aloof when neceſſity requires their ſuccour. Hiſtories make mention of one <hi>Vrſinus</hi> a Chriſtian Phyſician; who, beeing ready to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Martyrdome for the Goſpell, began to wauer and faint. Which, when <hi>Vitalis</hi> a holy man ſaw, hee ſtept to him; and, though hee knew it would coſt him his life, comforted and encouraged him. For the which, he alſo was condemned to death. <hi>Nic. de Lyra. Com. in</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. Few ſuch friends are now to be found, as will lay downe their liues for their Brethren. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Brethren reioice at the welfare and proſperitie one of another, and do wiſh as much happineſſe each to other as to themſelues. Thus ſhould Chriſtians, when we ſee God any waie good and gratious vnto our brethren, whether it be in matters of this life, or in matters of the life to come,<note place="margin">Exod. 18.9</note> reioice and bee glad thereat. <hi>Iethro</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiced at <hi>all the goodneſſe which the Lord had ſhewed vnto Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.57.58.</note> 
               <hi>Elizabeths</hi> neighbours and coſins did <hi>reioice with her when they heard tell that God had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mercy vpon her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.19.20</note> The <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> were <hi>Pauls ioy, and crowne of reioicing. Iohn</hi> reioiced greatly, when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16595:13"/>
he found the children of the elect Lady <hi>walking in the truth.</hi> And ſurely,<note place="margin">2 Iohn 4 3 Iohn 3.4</note> as <hi>Salomon</hi> diſcerned the true mother by her affection, ſo may wee a true Chriſtian by this marke. Woe then to ſuch, who haue no other cauſe of their ill will and malice towards their brethren, then this, that it goeth well with them, and God doth bleſſe them: As <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren hated him for no other cauſe, but for that his father ſeemed to loue him beſt. And ſo <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe God preferred <hi>Abel</hi> before him. Away with this ſame enuie, nouriſh it not within thee: <hi>It is the rottenneſſe of the bones,</hi> and ſo the iuſteſt of all vices, becauſe it bringeth with it its owne vengeance; as a Viper eating out the bowels where it is bred. It is a bloody ſinne,<note place="margin">Hier. in epiſt. ad Gal. c. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> for if it eate not out anothers heart, it will eate out thy owne. Be not an enemy to Gods fauours when they fall beſides thee: grudge not that thy neighbours field is fairer growne then thine. Quarrell not with God, becauſe thy neighbours flocke eſcapes the rot. Let not thy neighbours welfare bee thy diſeaſe: becauſe Heauen ſmiles on him, wilt thou look awry vpon him? becauſe God ſets on him the ſeale of his loue, wilt thou ſet on the ſeale of thy malice? Beware of that: Remember ſtill that hee is thy brother. And as the good of one member of the body, ſerueth for the vſe and profit of the other: So what hee hath ſhall tend to thy benefit, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine not for his vvelfare, but reioice thereat.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, Brethren, as they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16595:14"/>
with them that doe reioice, ſo they weepe with them that weepe. There is a ſympathy and fellow feeling of the miſeries each of other. If one be in heauineſſe the other cannot containe: Affection will then breake forth, and ſhew it ſelf. As we ſee in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 45.2.3</note> who albeit before he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled and hid it: yet when hee heares <hi>Iudah</hi> make ſuch a ſad relation, and ſees his brethren ſo ouerwhelmed with ſorrow, then compaſsion can be concealed no longer, Affection muſt breake forth violently at his voyce and eyes. He weeps aloud, and tells them he was <hi>Ioſeph their brother?</hi> Thus muſt it be with vs who profeſſe that we are children of God, and brethren of the faithfull. Yea, thus it will be with vs, if we are rightly bred and borne: As we ſee in <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe affection was ſo great towards his perſecuted brethren, as that he choſe rather to <hi>ſuffer affliction with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>then to enioy all the pompe and pleaſure of Pharaohs Court.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 1.2.3.4</note> So <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though he enioied much pleaſure and credit in <hi>Shuſhan</hi> in the Court of <hi>Artaxerxes;</hi> yet when he vnderſtood by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nani</hi> of the affliction and reproach of the people of God, all that pompe and glory could not ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his affection, but he muſt <hi>ſit downe and weepe and mourne, and faſt certaine dayes, and pray before the Lord of heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.18.29.</note> And ſo Saint <hi>Paul, The care of all Churches</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>commeth vpon me: who is weake and I am not weake? who is offended and I burne not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The want of this Affection ſheweth that wee are not brethren. So farre are we from weeping
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16595:14"/>
when they weepe, as that wee reioice at thoſe things which make them weepe. Wee can inſult ouer our brethren in the day of trouble,<note place="margin">Obad. 10.15</note> as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites</hi> did in the day of the deſtruction and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and ſpeake proudly againſt them in the day of their diſtreſſe. Or if we inſult not ouer ſuch as are in calamity, yet wee are no way touched with their miſerie.<note place="margin">Amos 6.4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Wee lye vpon beds of Iuorie and ſtretch our ſelues vpon our couches, and eat the Lambes out of the flocke, and the calues out of the midſt of the ſtall, we drinke wine in bowles, and anoint our ſelues with the chiefe ointments; but we are not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the afflictions of</hi> Ioſeph. Are not the bowels of the Saints wrung with grief; and the Church pinched with the perſecutions of her aduerſaries? Doo not the mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> of the world hunt her? And are not furrowes made vpon her backe with their ploughs? Look into the world, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the miſeries of the Churches in forrain parts; in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany:</hi> and, if thou haſt in thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpark of brotherly affection (nay, if thou haſt not put off the very nature of a man) thou muſt needs abate of thy pleaſures,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.2</note> &amp; with the captiue Iewes hang vp thy Harp vpon the willowes. <hi>The Ark, and Iſrael and Iudah abide intents;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.11</note> 
               <hi>and my Lord</hi> Ioab, <hi>and the ſeruants of my Lord are encamped in the open fields: ſhall I then go into my houſe,</hi> ſaid <hi>Vriah</hi> to <hi>Dauid, to eat and to drink, and to ly with my wife? As thou liueſt, and as thy ſoule liues, I will not do this thing.</hi> See, hee would not affoord to himſelfe any more then neceſſary contentment vnto nature, till hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16595:15"/>
ſaw the iſſue of that buſineſs.<note place="margin">Eſay 22.11.13 14</note> Shall we then feaſt, and ſport, and reuell? Shall joy and gladnes, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oxen, and killing ſheep, eating fleſh, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wine, be found amongſt vs in this day, when the Lord of Hoaſts cals to weeping and to mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to baldneſſe, and to girding with ſackcloth? Surely it will be reuealed in the ears of the Lord of Hoaſts: and this iniquity ſhall not bee purged from vs till we dy. Let vs not, my Beloued, think we haue the affections of children, when wee can ſee our mother ſick and ſorrowfull, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe. Let vs not think we haue the affections of brethren, when we can hear or ſee the maims and miſeries of Gods people, without laying them to heart. And therefore, as when the Church of God flouriſheth and houlds vp her head, we muſt lift vp ours, though otherwiſe it goeth not ſo wel with vs in our owne priuate eſtate and condition: ſo, when the Church mournes and hangs downe the head, wee muſt caſt downe ours, though our owne condition bee neuer ſo good. For, as the peace and proſperity of Ieruſalem ſhould ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our priuate grieuances; ſo her afflictions and dangers ſhould ſowre, and make diſtaſtefull to vs, all priuate comforts whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And thus wee haue ſeen the qualities and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Brethren: which if wee finde in our ſelues, it is no matter for the worlds mocking and ſcorning at this Brotherhood: it is our glory.</p>
            <p>If we conſider <hi>Paul,</hi> as a Miniſter, or an Apoſtle, ſo tearming them; then we thence note,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16595:15"/>Firſt, his great <hi>Humility.</hi> For, though many of them to whom hee wrote were poor and meane,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26</note> and ſuch as laboured with their hands, and few of them wiſe men after the fleſh, or mighty, or noble; and hee himſelfe a Miniſter of the word, yea an Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28</note> and ſo in the higheſt degree of the Miniſtery, and a planter of many Churches: yet he maketh himſelf equall to them of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſort, in calling them <hi>Brethren;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12</note> which is a word of <hi>equality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his great <hi>Mildeneſs</hi> and <hi>gentleneſſe of ſpirit,</hi> in that hee doth thus gently exhort them, when he had authority to command; and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates himſelf into them by ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pellation, the better to prouoke them to doo that they ſtood bound to doo.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his great <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> in vſing ſuch a kinde and louing tearm: wherby he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that hee did dearly and tenderly affect them in the Lord; and reſpect them as thoſe who were conjoined with him by the bond of one truth, one faith, and one hope of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>From the firſt wee inferre;<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1</hi> Miniſters muſt be humble. <hi>Luke 21.25.26</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Miniſters ought to behaue themſelues humbly in their places and callings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe lordſhip ouer them; and they that exerciſe authority vpon them are called Benefactours: But you ſhall not bee ſo: but hee that is greatest amongſt you, let him be as the youngeſt; and he that is chief, as though he did ſerue.</hi> The meaning of our Sauiour in which words, is, not to take away order, but to take away arrogancy and ambition.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16595:16"/>
Saint <hi>Peter</hi> giueth the like precept:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2.3</note> 
               <hi>Feed the flocke of God which is amongst you,  neither as being lords ouer Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>How then doth that ſame Antichriſtian ſpirit, vſurping authority with tyrannous vſage of Gods people, ſort with the Apoſtles precept and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? And that not onely of that Arch-prelate of Rome,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.4</note> who, vnder that title of <hi>Seruant of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God,</hi> aduanceth himſelfe aboue all that is called God: but alſo of others who are puft vp for their place and gifts,<note place="margin">3 Iohn 9.10</note> and with <hi>Diotrephes loue to haue the preheminence;</hi> and will neither receiue <hi>Iohn</hi> nor his Brethren. <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle equalles himſelf with them of the lower ſort. But now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould a change. Ordinary paſtors and they of the lower ſort doo not onely equall themſelues with, but euen aduance themſelues aboue Apoſtles; taking more vpon them than euer they did. <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> giues this report of <hi>Veſpaſian;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>C.</hi> Plinius. Epiſ. ad Veſpaſ. Nec quicquam in te mutauit fortunae ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo, niſi vt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe tantundem poſſes &amp; v lles.</note> That greatnes and majeſty changed nothing in him but this, that his power to doo good ſhould bee anſwerable to his will. And I would this alſo might bee truely ſaid of ſuch, who, either in reſpect of office in the Church, degrees in Schoole, riches in the world, or any ſuch-like outward prerogatiue, are aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced aboue their Brethren. Sure I am, if God ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance <hi>Heſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſt. 4.14</hi> Doct. <hi>2</hi> Courteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed rather than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it is that ſhee may bee a means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the Diſtreſſed of the Church of Cod.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee learne, that <hi>Courteous and gentle means are rather to be vſed by Gods Miniſters, than ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour or ſeuerity to perſwade men to obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16595:16"/>
               <hi>The ſeruants of the Lord muſt not ſtriue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24.25</note> 
               <hi>but be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle towards all men, in meekeneſse inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelues,</hi> ſayth <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi> And you ſhall finde him the ſame in practice that he was in doctrine, vſually comming to his hearers with <hi>I beſeech you Brethren by the mercies of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1 2 Cor. 10.1 2 Cor. 5.20. &amp; 6.1</note> 
               <hi>I Paul my ſelfe beſeech you, by the meekeneſſe and gentleneſſe of Chriſt. Wee Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you through vs, we pray you in Christs ſtead that you be reconciled to God.</hi> How ſweetly doth he practice his owne precept? And ſo Saint <hi>Peter, Dearely beloued, I beſeech you as Pilgrims &amp; Strangers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet 2.11. 2 Iohn 5</note> 
               <hi>abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, &amp;c.</hi> And thus Saint <hi>Iohn, I now beſeech thee Lady:</hi> So that wee ſee what meekeneſſe and mildneſſe we ought to vſe; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting and intreating, euen then when we may lawfully command. And no maruel, when God himſelfe herein goeth before vs in his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Oh that Iſrael would haue hearkned;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81 13 Mat. 23.</note> And our Sauiour Chriſt inuiting the Iſraelites in the ſame manner vnto himſelfe, that the Henne doth her chickens.</p>
            <p>Let this ſerue then for our <hi>Imitation</hi> and <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note> that we endeauour to win our people with gentleneſſe and loue. And ſurely when miniſters ſpeake thus to ſinfull men; <hi>I beſeech you by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, I beſeech thee my Brother,</hi> leaue thy whoredome, forſake thy drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. If the heart bee not ſealed vp with hardneſſe, it muſt needes pearce it. Wee ſee how in things of this life, men are faine to ſue for that which is their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16595:17"/>
owne, and are heart-glad if by fair intreaties they can gather vp their debts. If then we can by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt exhortations and effectuall perſwaſions get at our peoples hands this debt of obedience w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they owe to God, let it neuer grieue vs that wee come with <hi>Brethren, I beſeech you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cauca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note>And yet withall great wiſdom and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction muſt be vſed in this manner of proceeding: for, wee muſt beware, that wee ſo lay downe our authority, as that the word loſe not any; but abide ſtill a word of power to command. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe rules are to be obſerued:</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſo exhort and perſwade, as that the very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of men that hear thee may conclude, that euen there where thou intreateſt thou haſt power to command, although in loue thou laieſt downe that power for the preſent. So the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Philemon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 8.9</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore though I might bee much bould in Christ to enioyn thee that which is conuenient, yet for loues ſake I rather beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſo to exerciſe lenity, as that thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not ſeuerity when the caſe requireth it. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion muſt be had on ſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 23</note> but not on all: ſom muſt <hi>with fear be puld out of the fire.</hi> When ſinne waxeth bold, then muſt Gods Miniſters put on bouldnes; as <hi>Moſes</hi> did when the calfe ſtood before him. When the Miniſtery is like to bee brought into contempt, then muſt power and authority be put on.<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.13</note> Sometimes muſt Gods Miniſter deliuer the word as it were in a <hi>ſoft and ſtill voice;</hi> and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles hee muſt change his note, and lift vp his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16595:17"/>
               <hi>voice like a trumpet, and ſhew them their ſinnes. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 58.1 2 Cor. 10.2.8 Acts 13.10.11 1 Tim. 1.10</note> as occaſion ſerueth, can ſtand vpon his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and authority: hee can cenſure <hi>Elymas:</hi> hee can deliuer <hi>vnto Satan,</hi> as well as <hi>intreat</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Doct. The Miniſter ought tenderly to affect his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>2 Cor. 6.11</hi>
               </note> in that the Apoſtle calleth them Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; obſerue <hi>with what tenderneſſe of affection a Minister ſhould be deuoted to his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Corinthians, our mouth is open vnto you, our heart is made large,</hi> ſaith this our Apoſtle to this people to whom he now wrot. And,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.8</note> writing to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> he doth vehemently proteſt his ſincere &amp; feruent loue towards them. <hi>God is my record,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>how greatly I long after you all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.11</note> 
               <hi>in the bowelles of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Such was his loue alſo to the <hi>Romans:</hi> as he witneſſeth, when he ſaith, <hi>That he longed to ſee them, that hee might beſtowe ſome ſpirituall gift vpon them to ſtrengthen them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.7</note> Such was his loue alſo to the <hi>Theſſalonians:</hi> as appeares in that hee ſaith, <hi>Wee were gentle amongst you, euen as a Nurſe cheriſheth her children;</hi> not as a Nurſe mercenary, but as a nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Mother, whoſe affections are moſt tender. And a little after he ſaith thus; <hi>We exhorted you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 11</note> 
               <hi>and comforted and beſought euery one of you</hi> (as a Father doth his children). And, writing vnto <hi>Timothie,</hi> he chargeth him,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> That he ſhould bee <hi>an enſample</hi> of the beleeuers <hi>in word, in conuerſation, and in loue.</hi> Where hee notes the Paſtors duty, So to loue his people, as that they might learne by him to loue one another.</p>
            <p>If Miniſters ſhould examine what loue they<note place="margin">Vſe.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16595:18"/>
bear vnto their people; I fear, many would finde a great want of brotherly affection. How empty are their hearts of this hearty and vnfained loue, who ſeeke pretenſes of long abſence from their flocks? whereby the duties of teaching, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of life in their own perſons, are neglected. Surely, this loue ouerthroweth ordinary abſence, without juſt and conſcionable cauſes.<note place="margin">Lawfull cauſes of a Miniſters abſence from his flock.</note> I deny not, but there may be ſom occaſions, which may, and that lawfully, draw a Paſtour for a time from his people: as, when the publike ſeruice of the Chur. ſhall require it,<note place="margin">Alterius Eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſian e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſsitatibus euocat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vobis ſolitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtudium depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. Amb. Ser. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> for the ſettling and compounding variances and differences, and ſuch like profitable imploiments. Thus, when the neceſſity of other Churches calleth for help at a Paſtors hands, heer is a good occaſion of abſence. And vpon this ground, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> excuſeth himſelf vnto his flock. And ſecondly, when a Paſtor perſonally is ſought for, and cannot remaine amongſt his flock with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peril of his life: if the perſecution be not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, both of the people and Miniſter, but onely perſonal of the Miniſter alone; heer is then good cauſe of his abſence. So <hi>Athanaſius</hi> did leaue the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and hidde himſelf for the ſpace of ſix years in a dry ciſterne,<note place="margin">Quis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hi mira <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pto vt tio v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtat, quod non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t mana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me quaere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. Tripa. hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> and 4 moneths in his Fathers Tomb, and made this Apology for himſelf; <hi>Who can blame me, beeing miraculouſly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, that I did not caſt myſelf into their hands</hi> (that is, the Arrians) <hi>who ſought mee?</hi> Thirdly, when health of body ſhall require diſcontinuance for a time,<note place="margin">Phil 2.25.28</note> it is lawfull. This cauſe ſtaied <hi>Epaphroditus</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16595:18"/>
from the Church of the <hi>Philippians:</hi> whom, aſſoon as he was recouered, <hi>Paul</hi> ſent vnto them. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a Miniſter may vpon his neceſſary priuate oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions lawfully for a time bee abſent: as, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing neceſſary ſutes of law for defending of his right, which requires his perſonall attenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; or in attending ſom Courts of Iuſtice whither he is cited, and the like: heer are juſt and lawful cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And yet in theſe caſes,<note place="margin">Aug. Ep. <hi>188</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtines</hi> rule muſt be obſerued: There muſt bee a care had, that the Church be not left deſtitute; but the Paſtors ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be by others for that time ſuppli'd, and that by ſuch as are ſufficient to guide their people: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no ſuch bad choice of their Curates,<note place="margin">1 Kings 11.31.</note> as <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> did of his Prieſts; of the loweſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who were not Leuites, that is, not inſtructed in the Law of God; but of ſuch as are painefull, faithfull, and able to inſtruct. So, <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 24.14</note> going vp to the Mount, left <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> his Deputies. And thus <hi>Paul</hi> ſent <hi>Timotheus</hi> to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.2</note> to ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh and comfort them touching their faith; and left <hi>Titus</hi> at <hi>Creta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.5</note> to redreſſe the things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main. Yea, if he be ſincerely affected to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when the neceſſity is ſerued, hee will haue a deſire to returne and viſit his flock;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.11 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and hee will ſay with S. <hi>Paul, I long to ſee you.</hi> He will haue ſuch a deſire after them as is impatient of delaies (for ſo the word ſignifies w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth); and wil not be long detained, after once he can get to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed: but plaieth as the old-beaten Hare;<note place="margin">Ionga curſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lus, cubilibus ſuis emori. Eſponc. lib. <hi>3.</hi> digreſs. ad <hi>1.</hi> Tim. cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> beeing weary of long chaſing abroad, returns home, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16595:19"/>
dyeth in his owne borrough. I could wiſh then that ſuch as are negligent, would themſelues ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeriouſly conſider this, then giue others cauſe to complaine: for certainly want of loue to the flocke is the cauſe of wilfull abſence from the flocke.<note place="margin">Omnis negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſcens to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſibi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum gregem, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>umcitur ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum non ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re paſtorem. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſ. epiſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And hee who loueth not the flock, loues not him whoſe flocke it is: and therefore our Sauiour ſayth to <hi>Peter, If thou louest mee feed my ſheep.</hi> Wherupon (ſayth one) euery one negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently feeding the Lords flocke, ſo often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto him, is found not to loue the chief ſhepheard CHRIST IESVS.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note>But though wee feed not commonly by our ſelues, yet continually by our ſubſtitutes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</note>If the former occaſions cauſe thy abſence, this is good; as before I haue ſhewed: If not, it is no excuſe, vnleſſe thou couldſt loue Chriſt by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie and ſubſtitute. It was a ſaying of one <hi>Iodocus,</hi> ſometimes a famous preacher within the Realme of France, which hee did often inculcate in his Sermons (<note n="*" place="margin">Vſpence. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ibunt per vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios parad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſum; in perſona in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>os.</note> as one that often heard it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.) That ſuch as feede their ſheepe by Vicars (themſelues being negligent and idle) ſhall go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen by their Vicars, but into hell in their owne perſons: hee ſpake pleaſantly yet vttered the truth. But to conclude this vſe, <hi>Aaron</hi> was commanded to beare the names of the children of Iſraell vpon his ſhoulders,<note place="margin">Exo. 28.12.19</note> and vpon his heart, for a memorial before the Lord continually. To remember Miniſters, ſayth Biſhop <hi>Babington</hi> (of reſpectiue memorie) vpon the place, How deare
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16595:19"/>
vnto them the flocke committed to their charge ſhould be, euen grauen as it were in their breaſts, and euer in their minds to profit them, by all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes they may, that they may bee ſaued. Looke then we do ſo: for if we haue no ſhoulder nor boſome for them, Chriſt that great <hi>Shepheard of the ſheepe</hi> will finde no manſion for vs.</p>
            <p>A ſecond vſe of this point may be for people: let them learne to be perſwaded of the loue and good affection of their Paſtors toward them; and anſwere it againe with like loue and good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is a policie of the diuell, to driue men out of conceit with their Miniſter, and cauſe them to ſuſpect his loue and affection towards them: and all for this end, that they may leſſe profit by his paines. For well doth this enemy of mankinde know, that where there is no affection to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there will bee no regard of the preaching; where there is no liking to the man, there will follow a loathing of his Miniſterie. For the mind being foreſtalled with this conceit, <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister loues vs not,</hi> makes vs miſdeeme all things whatſoeuer are ſpoken, to ſuit with the malitious Fountaine from whence preiudice ſuppoſeth them to proceed (as when the palate is annoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome bitter humour, all things ſeeme bitter to the taſte) and hereby is the effect of the word much hindered. We ſee this in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Ahab</hi> toward <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Micaiah</hi> whom hee hated; and profeſſeth his enmity toward them,<note place="margin">1 Kings 21.19 20. &amp; 22.7.8.</note> and therefore deſpiſed the word that came from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16595:20"/>
their mouths. And without doubt here is a main reaſon why men profit not by the teaching of the word as they ought and might, Becauſe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge not the loue of their Teachers, and their tender affection ouer them for their good: eſpecially when they taxe and reproue them for their ſinnes, then they thinke he loues them not, nor careth for them, but ſpeakes out of malice and ſpleene, and ſo they hinder their profiting by his teaching.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.12, 13.</note> But, <hi>I beſeech you brethren to know them which labour amongst you, and are ouer you in the Lord, and admoniſh you; and to eſteem them very highly in loue for their works ſake.</hi> We haue done now with the Compellation: the Valediction followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>Farewell.</hi> It hath beene an ancient cuſtome, both amongſt the Iewes and Grecians, to begin and end Letters and Epiſtles with Salutations and Greetings; and therein they did wiſh, to their friends, that which they counted the chiefeſt good. And hence the Heathen, as they were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionated about the chiefe Good, ſo they did indifferently wiſh good things to their friends in their ſalutations. The <hi>Philoſophers</hi> wiſhed <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie:</hi> the <hi>Phyſicians health:</hi> The <hi>Common-people Ioy:</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> wiſhed <hi>peace:</hi> The <hi>Romans ſafety:</hi> And our <hi>Apostle</hi> here,<note place="margin">Doct. Common forms of ſalutation both by word of mouth and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</note> 
               <hi>welfare;</hi> vnder which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all bleſſings belonging to this life, or a better. From hence we learne, Common forms of Salutation and Greeting (both by word of mouth, and writing) are commendable, and are both ancient and Apoſtolicall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16595:20"/>A precept for this duty wee haue giuen vs by our Sauiour: <hi>When you come into an houſe ſalute it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.11</note> And againe, <hi>Into whatſoeuer houſe you enter, firſt ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.5 Ruth 2.4</note> 
               <hi>Peace be to this houſe.</hi> A paterne wee haue in <hi>Boaz:</hi> who, coming among his reapers, ſaid vnto them, <hi>The Lord be with you:</hi> and they anſwered him, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee</hi> (Yea, the Angels themſelues haue vſed forms of ſalutations). And in the Angel that came to <hi>Gedeon,</hi> who ſaluted him thus;<note place="margin">Iud. 6.12</note> 
               <hi>The Lord be with thee, thou valiant man:</hi> And in the Angell <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who came vnto the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.28</note> and ſaid vnto her, <hi>Hail, thou that art highly fauoured, the Lord is with thee.</hi> The Pſalmographer inſinuateth the commonneſs of this Chriſtian duty among Gods people, when he ſaith, <hi>They that go by,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 129.8</note> 
               <hi>ſay not ſo much as The Lord proſper you.</hi> And we ſhall finde the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to be very preciſe in the obſeruing of this point in all his Epiſtles; who oftentimes ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth down the greetings and ſalutations of others as well as his owne.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.4-17</note> The whole ſixteenth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Romans, in a manner, he ſpends in this kinde.</p>
            <p>But when the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſent his ſeruant <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi</hi> to the Shunamites houſe, he charged him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 2 Kings 4.29.</note> if he met any man, <hi>Salute him not; and,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.4</note> 
               <hi>if any man ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted him, not to anſwer him again.</hi> The ſame charge did our Sauiour giue to his Diſciples, when hee ſent them out to preach: <hi>Salute,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>no man by the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The intent and meaning of the Prophet and of our Sauiour in thoſe places,<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſp.</note> is not ſimply and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16595:21"/>
to forbid greeting and ſalutation; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enjoyn an omiſſion of the practice of thoſe duties of common curteſie and ciuility, ſo farre forth as they are a hinderance of the performance of waightier affairs, and other far more neceſſary duties. This then is their meaning: <hi>Rather then you ſhould any way hinder the quick diſpatch of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs laid vpon you, ſpeak to no man that you meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by the way.</hi> So then this makes nothing againſt this truth. Now for the vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Heer wee ſee, Religion and Chriſtianity doth not make men rude and ruſticall, as men of the world think and ſpeake. God hath his Ethicks, a doctrine of behauiour, in his word: whereby hee teacheth vs how to carry our ſelues wiſely and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilly towards all, and amongſt all. And therfore it is a ſlander caſt vpon religion by the father of lies, that it makes men clowniſh: for, Gods ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are taught better manners, than to neglect ſo much as ſalutations either in writing or ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And ſecondly, ſeeing it is a duty, and that ſo antient and ſo commendable; let vs conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly learn to perform it both by word &amp; writing. <hi>Whatſoeuer things are true, whatſoeuer things are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8</note> 
               <hi>whatſoeuer things are iuſt, whatſoeuer things are pure, whatſoeuer things are louely, whatſoeuer things are of good report,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle (of which nature, as wee haue ſeen, this is) <hi>think on theſe things to doo them.</hi> And let no man ſay, Theſe are ſmall &amp; ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der matters to be ſpoken of, and ſtood vpon: for, it is a duty we are all bound vnto; and our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16595:21"/>
is to bee ſhewed as well in the leaſt as in the greateſt matters. And therefore let euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian make conſcience of it, and of the manner of performing it; and let him look,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the <hi>Form</hi> of ſalutation,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Salutations muſt be firſt Holy.</p>
                  <p>Doct. <hi>Boys</hi> poſt.</p>
               </note> that it bee firſt <hi>holy,</hi> and not idle, profane, and vnſauory, as the ſalutations of ſwearers, ſwaggerers, and rude ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians for the moſt part are: not, a pox in ſtead of peace; nor, The diuell take you, for The Lord be with you; not ſwearing to ſtead of praying. But our Salutations are to be holy, heauenly; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are to craue the greateſt bleſſings that are at at the hands of God, and beg the chiefeſt good for the perſons we ſalute.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>hearty;</hi> and therfore not hollow,<note place="margin">Hearty.</note> nor formal and cuſtomary. Som there are that ſpeak friendly to their neighbours, but imagine miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in their hearts: as we ſee in <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 3.27.</note> who cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his inward malice with ſweet and ſugred ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations, and moſt treacherouſly murdered vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Abner,</hi> euen in the act of ſaluting him. The like was his dealing with <hi>Amaſa:</hi> for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 20.9</note> while hee ſaid vnto him, <hi>Art thou in health, my Brother,</hi> and took him by the beard with the right hand to kiſs him; with the other hand he ſmote him with the ſword, and ſhed out his bowels to the ground. And ſo <hi>Iudas</hi> can come with <hi>Hail Maiſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.49</note> as well as <hi>Gabriel</hi> with <hi>Hail</hi> Mary. Many ſuch wee haue, whom a man would judge to bee the flowre of curteſie, and to haue all complements of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in them: and yet notwithſtanding all is but a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16595:22"/>
mask and vizard to colour their hypocriſie. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there are, who (according to the worlds fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion) reſt themſelues onely in a company of idle ceremonies, and childiſh complements; ducking and imbracing, and the like: wherein conſiſts all the grace of their greetings. It is well and truely ſaid by one, that A handfull of old friendſhip is worth an arm full of this new curteſie: for, that which is the pith and marrow of Chriſtian ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> the lifting vp of the heart in deſiring the welfare of thoſe that wee ſalute, is growne out of faſhion. But let vs renew it, and not content our ſelues in vſing good and holy forms, as <hi>God be with you, God ſaue you, The Lord bleſſe you,</hi> or the like; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we vſe them in a holy maner, feeling our harts affected with <hi>reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> and inlarg'd in <hi>loue</hi> towards our <hi>Brethren;</hi> ſtill remembring, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations are praiers to God: and therefore our hearts muſt be lifted vp vnto him, and his Name on whom wee call muſt with all reuerence bee thought vpon. For, if we onely ſpeak of cuſtome, not minding what wee ſay, wee take Gods holie Name in vain;<note place="margin">Exod. 20.7</note> for which hee will not hould vs guiltleſſe. Such a fault this is, as ought to be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of humiliation vnto all; yea, to the very beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> And yet I cannot paſſe ouer this point without a third vſe; which is, <hi>Reprehenſion</hi> of ſuch as neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this either in whole or part, through wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or weakeneſſe. Some there are, who are ſo ſtrongly poſſeſſed, and rankly ouer-growne with malice and reuenge, that they will neither
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16595:22"/>
ſalute ſuch as they meet, nor anſwer ſuch as ſalute them. Theſe are poſſeſſed with a <hi>dumb diuell,</hi> which had need to bee caſt out by faſting and by praier.</p>
            <p>Others there are, and they of the better ſort, who take occaſion to neglect this duety, becauſe they are praiers; and therefore think it vnlawfull to ſalute paſſengers ordinarily with <hi>God bee with you,</hi> or <hi>The Lord bleſs you.</hi> For, ſay they, wee knowe not who they are we meet withall, neither knowe we whither they go, or about what: or if wee do, yet ſuddenly ſo to ſay, is a taking of Gods Name in vain; and ſo a ſinne moſt fearfull. To anſwer theſe; thus much:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5</note> Charity biddeth vs to thinke and hope the beſt in matters of vncertainty. But admit that he thou meeteſt with bee an vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and an alien from the common-wealth of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, yet greetings and common ſalutations are due to ſuch. Our Sauiour, as wee heard before, commanded his Diſciples whenſoeuer they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into <hi>any houſe,</hi> they ſhould ſalute the ſame;<note place="margin">Mat. 10.12</note> and gaue them a form of ſalutation, which they muſt vſe whether the Son of peace were there or no; ſaying, <hi>Peace bee to this houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.5</note> 
               <hi>And if the Sonne of peace be in the houſe, your peace ſhall com vpon it,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour; <hi>if not, your peace ſhall return vpon you.</hi> So then, wee ſee there is no hurt done whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wee ſalute. If they be the children of GOD whom we ſalute, then wee doo good vnto them; if not, we do good vnto our ſelues: for, that good we deſire may befall them, ſhall fall on our owne heads.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16595:23"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 2. Iohn 10.</note>But Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> forbiddeth vs to ſalute, or bid <hi>God ſpeed,</hi> to ſome; <hi>For if we ſhould bid them God ſpeed, we ſhould be partakers of their euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reſp.</note>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> there ſpeakes of dangerous Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, who did broach a contrary doctrine, and teach another Goſpell; and therefore, after once or twice admonition,<note place="margin">Titus 3.10.</note> were to be rejected, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles rule. Now ſuch as theſe we may not ſalute; leſt we ſeeme to giue the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and approbation to their bad proceedings and damnable opinions.</p>
            <p>Againe, thou knoweſt not what intent he hath, or where about he goeth: What then? yet, Thy <hi>God be with you,</hi> will doe no harme; much good it may. Doe hee intend any wicked action; as to <hi>rob,</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> or any ſuch like lewdneſſe? thy prayer may diuert him happily from his purpoſe: For who can act any wicked worke, ſo long as God is with him, to direct him by his Spirit? But it can neuer further him in his euill.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, though it be a prayer, yet our hearts may be lifted vp to God in the ſudden vſing of it: For howeuer our deuotion is ordinarily more ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we pray for our brethren in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: yet theſe ſhort ejaculations by the way, may be profitable to our brethren, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God. And though we doe not lift vp our hearts in the vſing of them, yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that for our failing in the manner, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is good ſhould be neglected, or left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>performed. Let vs ſtill do the one, and amend the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16595:23"/>
other: and ſo God will be well pleaſed, our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren profited, and our ſelues comforted. And ſo much be ſpoken for the manner of the Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The matter of it followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E perfect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> The firſt thing he exhorts them to, is perfection: And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is a twofold perfection, the one of parts, the other of degrees; it is the later that is heere meant, and not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. The point is,<note place="margin">Doct. Perfection ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured.</note> 
               <hi>Perfection ought to bee endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Our whole courſe of life ſhould be a progreſſe vnto it.</hi> Perfection, in regard of ſinne to bee purged out, In regard of grace to bee encreaſed and ſtrengthened, In regard of our actions and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ought to bee hard followed, and ſtriued after.<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore leauing the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let vs goe on vnto perfection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 13.20.21</note> ſaith the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the Hebrewes. And againe, <hi>Now the God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Make you perfect in euery good worke to doe his will.</hi> So the Apoſtle exhorteth theſe Corinthians in another place of this his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, to <hi>perfect holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note> And ſuch as his doctrine, ſuch was his practice:<note place="margin">Philip. 3.13.14</note> 
               <hi>This one thing I doe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>forgetting thoſe things which are behinde, and reaching forth vnto thoſe things which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16595:24"/>
are before. I preſſe towards the marke, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.8.11.12.</note> When Chriſt aſcended vp on high, he gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Euangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers. For what end? <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Till wee all come in the vnitie of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Sonne of God, vnto a perfect man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1. Theſſ. 4.1. 1. Cor. 9.24.</note>
               <hi>Christianitie,</hi> as we know, is compared to a <hi>way,</hi> and to a <hi>race:</hi> in which a man muſt not ſtand ſtill, but goe onward, if he would come vnto the end, and receiue the crowne. And <hi>Christians</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto <hi>Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.20.</note> and therefore muſt euer bee waxing and increaſing in ſtature; going forward in knowledge and in wiſdome;<note place="margin">Luke 2.52.</note> growing in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and in fauour with God and man, as did our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Diuers ſorts then are iuſtly to bee cenſured: firſt, Such as haue not yet begun well, nor entred as yet into a courſe of Chriſtianitie; but ſpend their dayes in fulfilling of their luſts, and in a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie forgetfulneſſe of Religion and godlineſſe. How is it poſſible a man ſhould be <hi>Perfectus,</hi> that was neuer <hi>Factus?</hi> make an end that neuer yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. How farre from practiſing the Apoſtles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is the Drunkeard, the Adulterer, the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, the Vſurer? What perfection aime theſe at, vnleſſe it it be to be perfect ſlaues to <hi>Satan,</hi> or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Diuels:<note place="margin">Perfecte vt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecti.</note> Theſe as yet are perfect imperfect ones. Let all ſuch ſpeedily beginne, that they may continue and end. It is impoſſible for him
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16595:24"/>
to be perfected, who is ſtill abortiue. Begin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, deferre no longer, leſt Gods end comes before your beginning. Early holineſſe (ſay ſome) prooues ripe corruption: but certainly, habitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prophaneneſſe prooues ranke damnation; delay is dangerous. Enter then into the way of pietie, and follow it; ſtriuing with all your powers, to grow vp to a <hi>perfect man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Christ,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort to be reproued, are ſuch, as haue begunne, but goe not on; Dwarfes and Dunſes in Religion, alwayes being one, ſtanding at a ſtay, not growing at all; notwithſtanding the great meanes God in mercie hath afforded them: Like to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſeuen leane kine,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.21.</note> who deuouring vp ſeuen fat ones, ſeemed as leane, and as lanke, and euil fauoured as euer they were before. Such as are no wiſer at fiftie then at fifteene; oh how we cenſure it in them! And ſuch Schollars as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many yeares teaching profit not, or are no better learned then they were the firſt day; How doe we condemne? And yet this is the eſtate of many thouſands amongſt vs: of whom wee may ſay, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of thoſe ſilly women laden with ſinnes, and led away with diuers luſts,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>They are euer learning, and neuer able to come to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge of the truth.</hi> They remaine in the Schoole-houſe of Chriſt; heare Sermon after Sermon; haue leſſon after leſſon;<note place="margin">Eſay 28.10.</note> 
               <hi>precept vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept; line vpon line; heere a little, and there a little:</hi> yet neuer a whit bettered in their knowledge; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16595:25"/>
in faith, further'd in ſanctification of life: but, where you left them this year, you ſhall finde them the next, yea many years after; if not much worſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Much like <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> in <hi>Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who for <hi>30</hi> years together would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, ſhe was a year older.</note> The time of their life, and years of their age proceed and haſten vnto an end: yet they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour not to make a progreſs in godlineſs, they ſtriue not at perfection, but thinke they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and made progreſſe ſufficient; whereas all of vs ſhould prouide, that as the outward man decaieth, ſo the inward man ſhould bee renewed; and as the body is weakned, ſo the ſpirit ſhould be ſtrengthened. Theſe are like to the Sunne in <hi>Ioſuah</hi>'s time, that ſtood ſtill and moued not.</p>
            <p>A third ſort to bee reproued, are ſuch as haue begun well, and held on for a while, but now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coil like <hi>Zarah</hi> in <hi>Thamars</hi> womb; <hi>Apoſtates, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders,</hi> who return to their ould ſinnes, and ſtart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a deceitfull bowe, as if they neuer had bin the men:<note place="margin">Dan. 2</note> reſembling <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> image, whoſe head was of gold, and whoſe feet were of dirt; beginning gloriouſly in the ſpirit, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhamefully in the fleſh, as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the Galatians. Many there are that haue ſet out very freſh, like ſome pamperd jade, which at firſt is ſo free that no ground wil hold; but ſoon after giue in and tire. Of how many may it bee ſaid, They haue been forward, zealous, carefull in the waies of godlineſs,  but now the world hath choaked them, the vanity thereof beguiled them, they are not the men they haue been? Alas for ſuch!<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2 22</note> in as much as they are becomne very
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16595:25"/>
dogs and ſwine. The diuell himſelfe can ſay hee hath been good: but what is hee the better? nay, he is much the worſe. God will reward vs in the preſent tenſe, not in the preterperfect tenſe; as we are, not as we haue been. It were ſurely better for ſuch, neuer to haue knowne the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, than, after they haue knowne it,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21</note> thus to turn from the holy commandement deliuered vnto them.<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe are like the Sun in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>echiahs</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e that went back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> All theſe come far ſhort of the Apoſtles precept, <hi>Be perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which rule let vs all walk; and reſolue, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour, contend, and ſtriue for perfection, as for a prize; adding <hi>grace to grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1 Pſal. 84</note> 
               <hi>and growing from <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ſtrength to ſtrength.</hi> As the waters ſpoken of in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel</hi> grew vp by degrees, firſt to the ankles, then to the knees, then to the loines, and laſtly to the head: ſo let vs be <hi>perficientes,</hi> going and growing vp; that at the laſt we may bee <hi>perfecti,</hi> made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect men in Chriſt. Proficiency is comfortable, and a pledge that the Lord will perfect what hee hath begun. And, to ſtir vs vp vnto this duty, let vs conſider how naturall things doo affect, and in their manner long after, the perfection of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. The infant is ſtill growing in the womb, vntill it come to a perfection: and ſo, plants and other liuing creatures; wee ſee what little begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings they haue, yet they neuer ceaſe mounting till they attaine their due perfection. As nature hath put this property into ſuch things as are by her made vnperfect, whereby they enlarge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and growe out to the perfection which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16595:26"/>
doth agree vnto their kinde: ſo hath grace much more this property, that albeit it hath weake and ſmall beginnings; yet if true, it will growe as a grain of muſtard-ſeed,<note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31</note> and increaſe mightily. It may then juſtly bee feared, that thou haſt not the truth of Chriſtianity, who haſt not a deſire &amp; lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after the perfection of Chriſtianity: and thou that dooſt not aime at the perfection of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, haſt not in truth the perfection of parts.</p>
            <p>As for abſolute and Angelicall perfection, it is not to be expected in this world. It was the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Nouatus</hi> and <hi>Pelagius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.42</note> who boaſted of ſuch a purity, and gaue the name of Puritans vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Our perfection is in part, not wholly; in reſpect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Imperfecta per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio.</hi> Phil. 3.13.14</note> not abſolute. An imperfect perfection ours is: and this it is; <hi>To acknowledge imperfection, and ſtriue hard toward the mark</hi> (which is the thing that now we preſſe) as the Apoſtle ſheweth. For the attainment of which,<note place="margin">Meant to attain perfection. <hi>Phil. 3.13</hi>
               </note> theſe directions may be auaileable: Firſt, learn to <hi>forget that which is behind, and look on that which is before.</hi> Think not ſo much of what thou haſt attained, as what remains to be atchieued: look not ſo much on what thou haſt done, as on what remaines by thee to bee done. This is a good courſe, Often to conſider how far ſhort thou art of that thou ſhouldeſt be.</p>
            <p>Secondly: Compare thy ſelf with thy ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, rather than with thy inferiors, in grace: we often look vpon o hers far behinde vs, and That cauſeth vs to think wee need not ſo beſtirre our ſelues. And hence it is that we ſeem to our ſelues
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16595:26"/>
               <hi>half-Angels,</hi> becauſe we are not (as ſome others) <hi>half-diuels.</hi> Such a deceit is this (ſaith one) as that of Drapers, who commend a kerſey by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to a rug. Our knowledge is thought ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboundant, becauſe it is more then what our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had; neuer conſidering that our meanes are more, and therfore God looks for more from vs. And this cauſeth many to ſit downe, and reſt themſelues contented with what they haue. And yet in things of this life men do not thus: for, what man, hauing a competent eſtate, will caſt his eye vpon a begger that hath nothing; and thereupon conclude, He is rich enough, he will now giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer trading? Rather he wil ſet before him one ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher than himſelfe, to prouoke him to greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence: And ſo let vs ſet before our eies the moſt eminent amongſt Gods Saints (as, <hi>Abraham, Iob, Dauid, Moſes</hi>) yea God himſelfe; that ſo our dull fleſh may be ſpurred on, and we cauſed to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to <hi>be perfect, as he is perfect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.48</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, bee daily conuerſant in the reading, hearing and meditation of holy Scriptures: for, they are giuen by inſpiration of God for this end, <hi>That the man of God may be perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.17</note> 
               <hi>throughly furniſhed vnto all good works.</hi> What might wee come to in Chriſt, if wee would daily ſtudy the Scriptures, and meditate therein continually? for want of which, we grow ſo ſlowly. The neglect of labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at this oar cauſeth vs to go downe the winde and tide.</p>
            <p>Theſe means let vs vſe, that we may attain vnto
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16595:27"/>
perfection.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6</note> And as the kine of the Philiſtines, which drew the Ark of God, though they were milch and had calues at home; the one to weaken them, the other to withdraw them: yet, without turning to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or left, they kept on their way til they came to <hi>Bethſhemeſh:</hi> ſo, hauing once joined our ſelues to the yoak of Chriſt, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Ark of his law vpon our ſhoulders in the way of a vertuous life; though we haue many hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances (worldly allurements, the diuels temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and our owne ſinfull prouocations) yet let vs keep on the way of godlineſs, being not like the old Moon in the wane, but like the new in her increaſe; and like the morning light, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> groweth brighter and brighter to perfect day: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that as God is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> ſo hee will haue his ſeruants to runne from <hi>Alpha</hi> to <hi>Omega,</hi> from the beginning to the ending in the conſtant profeſſion of the faith. Pray therefore for perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: and look to thy ſelf that thou loſeſt not the things which thou haſt done, but that thou maiſt receiue a full reward. And ſo we paſs from this duty vnto the next.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>Bee of good comfort.</hi> The Apoſtle well knew with how many diſcouragements they were to meet withall (for there is no calling nor duty but hath his croſſes attending.) <hi>Without;</hi> the world, ſometimes ſcoffing at their piety, and laughing it out of countenance; otherwhiles threatning; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles vexing; alwaies labouring to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; few to accompany; many to oppoſe. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16595:27"/>
conſcience of infirmitie and imperfection: which is ſo ſtrong and preualent with many, that they become weary of well doing, becauſe they are weake in doing. And therefore the Apoſtle willeth them to comfort their hearts one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother iointly; and each one ſeuerally, that they might be able to withſtand in the euill day, and not make ſhipwracke of their faith when any boiſterous tempeſt and ſtorme of temptation did ariſe. The point that naturally ariſeth out of the words (to paſſe by others) is:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtians ought mutually to comfort one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct. Chriſtians ought mutually to om ort one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</note> 
               <hi>and to be comforted one by another.</hi> This is the ſcope of the Apoſtle and the ſenſe of the words, as wee haue ſeene at the beginning in the Expoſition. For further proofe and confirmation, read what is ſayd in the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah. Comfort ye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 40.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye my people, ſayth the Lord God: ſpeake yee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to Ieruſalem.</hi> And in the Prophecie of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaniah</hi> thus read we: <hi>Sing O Daughter of Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zoph. 3.14</note> 
               <hi>ſhout O Iſraell be glad and reioice with all the heart O Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.11</note> And in the ſame Pſalme which the ſweet ſinger of Iſraell penned to giue inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (as the title hath it) the righteous are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with this duty: <hi>Be glad in the Lord, and reioice ye Righteous, and ſhout for ioy all yee that are vpright in heart:</hi> and elſewhere thus; <hi>Let Mount Sion reioice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 48.11</note> 
               <hi>and let the daughter of Iuda be glad.</hi> And in the new Teſtament our Apoſtle doth often vrge it.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.18 <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.11 Verſe 14</note> 
               <hi>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comfort yee one another. Wherefore comfort your ſelues together. Wee exhort you Brethren to comfort
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16595:28"/>
the feeble minded, ſupport the weake.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter,<note place="margin">Verſe 16.</note> he doth enioine a continual reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: <hi>Reioice euermore;</hi> In all eſtates, aduerſe or proſperous, in whatſoeuer condition God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to place vs in.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.4</note> So is the precept; <hi>Reioice in the Lord alwaies, againe I ſay reioice:</hi> hee doubles the <hi>Mandate,</hi> to ſhew the neceſſitie of the dutie. And this was the end of <hi>Leuiticall Feſtiuities.</hi> Thus wee haue ſeene this point prooued: <hi>viz. Chriſtians ought mutually to comfort one another, and to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one of another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note>And good reaſon: For ſorrow is a gulfe, and ſwallowes vp many when comfort is wanting: as the Apoſtle ſheweth to theſe Corinthians,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.7</note> when hee requireth them to forgiue and comfort that excommunicated perſon. The diuell is ſubtill: and when any of Gods children are in perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then he laboureth to take moſt aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; as experience maketh good.</p>
            <p>The vſes follow hereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>confutation</hi> of their ſottiſh opinion, who thinke no ioy nor comfort belongs to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; and that the life of a man, fearing God, is a dumpiſh and melancholy life. And why ſo? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot take pleaſure in vanitie, and laugh and be merry in things ſinfull. Surely, that which is a carnall mans greateſt mirth is vſually the greateſt ſorrow of a Chriſtian, and makes his heart to melt for griefe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> Hall <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 8</note> The world is like an ill Foole in a play: the Chriſtian is a iudicious ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatour,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16595:28"/>
who thinkes thoſe ieſts too groſſe to bee laught at; and therefore entertaines that with ſcorne, which others with applauſe. But haue they then no ioy? Yes, matter of great ioy.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.15</note> 
               <hi>The voice of reioicing and ſaluation, is in the Tabernacles of the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who more heauy and vnchearefull,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> more ſad and ſorrowfull? experience ſhewes it: that we ſee; their ioy we ſee not. True:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R ſ.</hi> Pro. 14.10.</note> For <hi>the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall not enter into his ioy,</hi> they ſhall not meddle with it, nor can they diſcerne it; It being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and requires an internall eye, the eye of Faith to diſcerne it with. And for their ſorrow, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee denied but the Godly are oft-times more ſorrowfull then they haue cauſe. And yet when they haue cauſe their joyes are an hundred fold more than their ſufferings.<note place="margin">Mark 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note> And their greateſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is but as a painted ſorrow in compariſon of the ſorrow of the wicked: and therefore ſayth the Apoſtle, <hi>As ſorrowfull, yet alwaies reioicing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> maner of ſpeech is wel obſeru'd by one,<note place="margin">Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n loc.</note> and is worthy to be obſerued by all. He bringeth in the <hi>ſorrow</hi> of the Godly with a <hi>quaſi, as it were ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe;</hi> not that it is ſorrow indeed, but ſayth he, <hi>As ſorrowfull:</hi> but when he ſpeakes of <hi>Ioy,</hi> there is no <hi>quaſi,</hi> but true ioy. The <hi>Sorrow</hi> of Gods Children then hath a <hi>quaſi,</hi> their <hi>Ioy</hi> hath none. But now, <hi>è contra,</hi> the wicked worldling is moſt miſerable; For his <hi>Ioy</hi> hath a <hi>quaſi,</hi> but his <hi>ſorrowes</hi> are without. They are ſorrowes to good earneſt: and therefore they are bidden to <hi>howl</hi> and <hi>lament,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:16595:29"/>
to weep and roar,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames 5.1</hi> Florent ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, pertunt in aeternum: flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent falſis bonis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereunt veris tormentis Aug o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pſal. <hi>5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for thoſe ſorrowes that ſhall come vpon them.</hi> They flouriſh and joy for a time, but they periſh and mourne for euer, ſaith a Father: they joy in falſe &amp; deceiueable good things, and they periſh in true and remedileſſe torments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Redargution</hi> or <hi>Reprehenſion:</hi> firſt, of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ſuch as fail in their duty, in not giuing comfort; ſecondly, of ſuch as fail as much in their duty, in not taking comfort when it is giuen. Of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſort there are degrees. Some there are that will giue comfort, but not to all; or at leaſt not in that manner and meaſure as is fitting. Let ſome of the wealthier ſort be in any trouble, then there is riding, running, ſending, going, pitying, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and, as mice and rats, they run to the Barne w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is full of corn: but he that is poor, is hardly acknowledged of his brethren,<note place="margin">Pro. 19.4.7</note> much leſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; or if he be, it is very coldly: few words are ſpoken whereby his wearied and perplexed ſpirit may be refreſhed. Will you hear the vſuall form of comforting? I am ſorry, neighbour, to ſee you thus, ſay ſome. I hope to ſee it otherwiſe with you ere long, ſay others; I ſhould bee ſorry elſe: I haue ſeen others as lowe brought as you, yet haue done well enough. And heer is all. As for deeds, it may be ſome rich Chuff may ſend-him-in a pot of pottage, or a groat; and think hee hath done a work of ſupererogation in ſo doing. Heer is ſory comfort to refreſh the bowels of the ſaints withall in the day of their diſtreſſe. Others there are that giue gall for meat, and vineger to quench
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16595:29"/>
thirſt; as the Iewes, our Sauiour: adding afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them whom the Lord hath wounded, by inſolencies &amp; exprobrations; as <hi>Shemei</hi> to <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 16.13.</note> Of the ſame ſpirit, amongſt vs wee haue many; who triumph in the greateſt miſeries of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. That miſery of miſeries, a wounded ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, many make it rather matter of exprobration than of compaſſion: This is the fruit of your Church-gadding and Sermon-following; or elſe by queſtioning ſincerity, as the friends of <hi>Iob.</hi> See, ſay they, now God hath met with him, he is paied home for his hypocriſie, &amp;c. Of ſuch as theſe may be truly ſaid. <hi>Miſerable comforters are you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let all ſuch miſcreants remember and hear their doom which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> denounces againſt them by Propheticall inſtinct.<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.24.26</note> 
               <hi>Poure out thine indignation vpon them, and let thy wrathfull anger take hould vpon them: for, they perſecute him whom thou haſt ſmitten, and they talk to the grief of thoſe whom thou hast wounded.</hi> Goe on then, thou that art ſo barbarous &amp; inhumane: laugh at the Religious: ſport thy ſelfe with their ſorrows: make thy ſelfe merry with their miſeries; and count it melody, To ſee and hear of the maladies of thy Brethren: Yet knowe, that <hi>light is ſowne for the righteous, and ioy for the vpright in heart.</hi> But, as thou haſt done,<note place="margin">Obad 15</note> ſo ſhall it bee done to thee: thy reward ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly return vpon thy owne head. For, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort that this doctrine meets with, are thoſe who doo not fail in giuing, but in not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16595:30"/>
comfort when it is offred. You ſhall heare theſe often effectually comforting others that are in miſery, and liberally drawing out of the <hi>wels of conſolation</hi> for others that are afflicted; yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will take none. May not the prouerb be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed to theſe? <hi>Phyſician, heal thy ſelf.</hi> They will ſpend much time in making knowne their wants, but will not apply the remedy. No argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be ſtrong enough to make them chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;<note place="margin">Mat. 2.18</note> but, as <hi>Rachel</hi> weeping for her children, they will not bee comforted. And why ſo? Becauſe they are vnworthy of ſuch gratious promiſes. But doe not thou ſtay till thou bee worthy: take the comfort that is brought, and be thankfull. Wee would count him mad, that being fallen into ſom pit, and nigh to drowning, calling and crying out for help, ſhould yet when help is offred withdraw his hand becauſe hee hath done nothing worthy of that loue and kindnes. Look thou to thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions that are required in Gods word, and ſee thou bee capable of thoſe comforts; and neuer ſtand vpon thy owne deſert or merit: for, though it bee too much for thee to haue, yet it is not too much for God to giue.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Inſtruction to the performance of this duty. Firſt, mutually one another; and ſecondly, euery one himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iob 6.14.</note>
               <hi>Man that is in miſery ſhould bee comforted of his friends,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, but that men haue forſaken the fear of the Almighty.</hi> You then that haue this feare of God before your eies, make conſcience of this
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16595:30"/>
duty: and as you deſire to partake comfort from God, ſo with-hould it not from the afflicted. It is reported of the Bees, that when one is ſick,<note place="margin">Aegrotante vna lamentantur omnes. Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> they all mourn: and of the Sheep, that if one of them be faint, the reſt of the flock will ſtand betweene it and the Sunne, vntill it bee reuiued. God hath hewen vs all out of one rock, tempered all our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of one clay, and ſpirited our ſoules of one breath. We are all ſons of one Father, members of one body, and heirs of one Kingdome: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of which neer linking together, ther ſhould be compaſſion and ſympathy betwixt vs.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.26</note> 
               <hi>If one member grieue, all ſuffer with it,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. And doo we not ſee, when a thorn is got into the foot, how the back bows, the eyes pry into the hurt, the hands are buſie to pluck out the cauſe of the anguiſh: <hi>Euen wee are members one of another;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.29 Pſal. 41.1.2 2 Tim. 1.16.17</note> and therefore be it ſo. So ſhall God recompenſe it into thy boſome; and the ſoules of the afflicted bleſſe thee.</p>
            <p>And for our ſelues: Let vs chear vp our hearts, and not darken the glory of religion by our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable walking. If worldlings offend, that they laugh when they ſhould mourn; wee offend no leſſe, if wee droop in cauſe of chearfulneſſe. And what eſtate can we be in, wherein wee haue not cauſe of chearfulneſſe, if wee bee the Lords? If both earth and hell ſhould conſpire to afflict and moleſt thee; yet if thou haſt God thy Father, Chriſt thy Sauior, the holy Spirit to be thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, and Heauen for thy manſion: thy ſorrow
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16595:31"/>
cannot counteruail the cauſes of thy joy. Thy loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, croſſes, may be great: but thy joies do far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.21</note> 
               <hi>Enter into thy maſters ioy,</hi> ſaid the Lord vnto his ſeruant that was faithfull. Great joy it muſt be, becauſe our <hi>Maſters;</hi> and becauſe that enters not into vs, but we into it: ſuch, which we cannot comprehend, but are comprehended of it. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily then is it called <hi>Ioy vnſpeakeable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and full of glory.</hi> In time of grief then put <hi>Dauids</hi> queſtion to thy heart, <hi>Why art thou ſad, my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within mee?</hi> Weigh all things well in the balance of the Sanctuary; and, I dare ſay, thou wilt not knowe whether to bee more angry with thy ſelf, or more aſhamed at the anſwer. It may be it is thy body, or thy purſe, or thy fame, or thy friends, that cauſeth that vnchearfulneſſe: it may bee none of theſe; onely thou art ſad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art. But what if theſe, or more?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hall</hi> Dec.</note>Yet, haſt thou God? If yea, Why then doeſt thou not reioice? Canſt thou freeze in the fire, and ſtarue at a feaſt? He is the authour of all true ioy, how canſt thou be dumpiſh? Haſt thou the conduit of Comfort and yet abid'ſt in heauineſs? <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> they ſang in the priſon: The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in the ſlames: <hi>Iohn Baynam</hi> reioyced, as if hee had been in a bed of Roſes, when hee was at ſtake. No doubt, theſe were ſenſible of the pain: but the ſweetnes of that joy, which they had ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the fruition of God and his fauour, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame the feeling of their preſent torments.</p>
            <p>Suffer not then thy ſelfe ſo to be vanquiſhed or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16595:31"/>
diſmaied by any grieuance whatſoeuer, as that thou ſhouldeſt not be able chearfully to ſerue the Lord. And ſo I come to the next thing the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts vnto; and that is <hi>Vnanimity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be of one minde.</hi> In which words,<note place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſſenſions that were amongſt them are noted out; and they exhorted to vnanimity and conſent in matters of faith and doctrine. The note is: <hi>Such as profeſſe one and the ſame faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould minde and affect the ſame things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of the former Epiſtle which hee wrote to the Corinthians as well as in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of this, wee ſhall finde the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending this duty to them; thinking it to bee ſo neceſſary, that both in the beginning and in the end, and at all times, they were to be put in mind of it. <hi>Now I beſeech you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Brethren</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame things a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that there bee no diuiſions amongst you; but, that ye bee perfectly ioyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in his epiſtle to the Romans, the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaue one, hee makes a moſt earneſt praier to God, that this might be found among them; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.5</note> 
               <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation grant you to be alike-minded one towards another, according to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ; that you may with one minde, and with one mouth, glorifie God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil 2.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And writing to the Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, hee doth deeply charge them (yea, ſtrongly adjure them) that <hi>If there were any conſolation in Christ, any comfort of loue, any fellowſhip of the ſpirit,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16595:32"/>
if any bowels and mercies; fulfill yee my ioy, that yee bee like-minded, hauing the ſame loue, beeing of one accord, and of one minde.</hi> Were not this a duty of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, ſurely the Apoſtle would neuer bee ſo earneſt in the vrging of it; beſeeching, praying, yea adjuring vs to the practice of it. And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>For a great aduantage is giuen to the enemy by diſſenſion: It is a military principle, <hi>Tempt not an enemy by giuing him the aduantage.</hi> Wee giue them opportunity to ſhuffle-in their counterfeit coine, whiles we conſent not in our gold: (And yet alas the difference amongſt vs is not ſo much about the weight or purenes of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as about the faſhion.<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt.</note>) And this, <hi>Euſebius</hi> obſerues, was the policie of the ſubtill ſerpent, when perſecutions gaue the Church breathing ſpace, Euermore to begin to vexe her with her owne diuiſions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Alas for vs! for there is vtterly a fault amongſt vs in this reſpect. As for diuiſion in Doctrine, which is Hereſie, we cannot be charged with; but for diuiſion in rites, which is Schiſme, that is our diſeaſe. In ſubſtance we ioine, and therefore thinke it a ſmall matter to diſſent in circumſtance: and indeed it is the leſſe matter; yet ſuch a matter as deſerues a ſharpe cenſure: what detriment it hath been vnto our Church, hee hath no mind that conſiders not, no heart that condoles not. Shee hath beene like <hi>Rebecca,</hi> troubled in her wombe with the ſtriuings of two children of contrary diſpoſitions: which hath cauſed her to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16595:32"/>
complaine, <hi>Why am I thus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> is againſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim.</hi> Woe to ſuch vnnaturall brethren who pittie no more the paines of their mother. Surely the Authors and Fautors of her diuiſion haue much to anſwere for before the Lord. For the ſinne is ſo great, if we beleeue <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (eſpecially authoritie being reſiſted) that it cannot bee expiated by Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Let it therefore admoniſh and exhort as many <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> as loue the peace of <hi>Sion,</hi> to bee knit together in one mind and one iudgement in the Lord. Read how many vnities the Apoſtle puts vs in mind of, that we might be the better wonne to this vnitie:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>There is one Body, one Spirit, one Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we ſerued diuers Lords &amp; Maſters, there might ſometimes naked ſwords be ſeen: but now contentions muſt needs be odious.</p>
            <p>Againe conſider, Is it not a ſhame for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God to diſſent, when the children of hell are at peace? The diuels in hell are not diuided: and it is neceſſary for them to hearken one vnto another (ſaith a Father) and to haue vnity in their diſtraction, leſt they ruine their owne kingdome.<note place="margin">Expedit ipſis daemon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> libi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mat A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> For a kingdome, nay that very kingdome being diuided againſt it ſelfe could neuer ſtand. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conſider the effects that follow heereupon. The diuiſion of tongues, as we read in holy writ, hindred the building vp of <hi>Babell:</hi> and it cannot otherwiſe bee but the diuiſion of hearts muſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16595:33"/>
needs hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding of our Ieruſalem: Gods Sabbot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eglected: the Word, the Goſpell of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Ieſus, cannot haue that free paſſage, that it otherwiſe could and would haue, were it not for our owne home-bred broyles. Some wil heare none but refuſers of conformity: others take aduantage of their diſobedience, to contemne their Miniſtery: both waies, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt is hindred. It giueth likewiſe matter of encouragement vnto our enemies. How commeth it to paſſe (ſay Papiſts to vs) you haue ſo many ſects amongſt you? What meane the tearmes of <hi>Zuinglians, Lutherans, Caluiniſts?</hi> How is it that ſome are <hi>Browniſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Baraiſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Puritans,</hi> ſome <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> How happens it, that touching Ceremonies &amp; Diſcipline (Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee God, they can taxe vs in no other) there is ſuch diſagreement?<note place="margin">Strom l. <hi>7.</hi> Quia Omnia ſecta chriſtianiſmi ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulum ſibi ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cat, tamen alia altam exceratur &amp; condemnat.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> brings in the Heathen, exprobrating our religion for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, vnwarrantable; vpon this very ground.</p>
            <p>Thus it giueth aduantage to our enemies to ſcorne vs; yea, and more, to ſcourge vs. Aske the reaſon why the wild Boare hath ſpoyled the vineyard; why the <hi>Iim</hi> and <hi>Zijm,</hi> filthie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane birds, rooſt themſelues within our ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Dominions. The anſwere muſt be, Iſrael is not true to <hi>Iudah:</hi> the renting of the ten Tribes from the two, hath made both the tenne and the two, miſerable: <hi>Scilurus</hi> his arrows, taken ſingly out of the ſheaf, are broken with the leaſt finger: the whole bundle vnſeuered feares no ſtreſſe. By
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16595:33"/>
diſperſing our forces we have weakned our ſelues: and thus we haue found the Politicians rule to be but too true; Make diuiſion, and get dominion.<note place="margin">Diui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra. amicorum diſpendia hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> compendia.</note> Diſſenſions haue beene, and are, a Lent to our friends, a Chriſtmas to our foes; gain to the one, and loſſe vnto the other. To draw now to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this point: Let it be enough (yea, and more than enough) that our falling out hath been a grief and heart-ſmart to our mother: let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further, leſt we all ſmart for it in the end. So ſhall the peace of our Ieruſalem break forth as the light; and the ſaluation thereof, like the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Sun. Let vs be guided by that one rule w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God hath preſcrib'd in his word; and not decline from that, either to the right hand or to the left. In ſuch things as are not reuealed, let vs a-while ſuſpend our judgements; and wait GOD's good pleaſure for the reuelation of them: and,<note place="margin">Text. Prius pertinet ad opinionum conſenſum: vt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cet idem de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de &amp; dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Alcerum eſt mutua ſe cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritate &amp; amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum coniunctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne complecti. Cal. in loc.</note> to thoſe things that are reuealed, let vs hold faſt. And this is the way to haue the joy of our Sion full.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liue in peace.</hi> As the former precept had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to matters <hi>Eccleſiaſticall;</hi> ſo this, to things ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: whether <hi>Politicall,</hi> as between neighbour and neighbour, ſuperiour and inferiour; or <hi>Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> which is to be practiſed in the priuate family between the husband and the wife, the parent &amp; the childe, the maſter and the ſeruant, &amp;c. The obſeruation is this:<note place="margin">Doct. Chriſtians are to liue peaceably one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtians are to lead a peaceable and a quiet life one with another.</hi> All diſcord and contention is to bee auoided, euen in ciuill and externall things: and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16595:34"/>
peace and quietneſs is to be followed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct. <hi>Hall</hi> Rom. irrecon ſect. <hi>2</hi>
               </note>There is nothing (ſaith a Worthy of our times) which the Angels did more gladly congratulate vnto men, or which Chriſt did more carefully bequeath, or the Apoſtles more earneſtly enjoyn, than this practice of peace. How oft, and how ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently, doth the Spirit intreat and command vs to haue peace, and to imbrace it? Wee are commanded to loue and affect it:<note place="margin">Zach. 8.19</note> 
               <hi>Loue the truth, and peace.</hi> Neither is it ſufficient to loue, but wee are enjoined to ſeek it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 34 14</note> 
               <hi>Depart from euil and do good, ſeek peace and enſue it.</hi> Neither is this ſufficient to ſeek it, but we muſt alſo haue it: <hi>Haue ſalt in your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 9.50</note> 
               <hi>and haue peace one with another.</hi> But what if peace will not be had? what then? S. <hi>Iames</hi> then chargeth vs to <hi>make peace</hi> by our endeauours,<note place="margin">Iames 3.18</note> by our patience. <hi>The fruit of righteouſnes is ſowen in peace of them that make peace.</hi> But, if in caſe it be once made and had, what if it will not ſtay nor abide with vs?<note place="margin">Rom 14.19</note> Then, ſaith S. <hi>Paul, Follow after the things which make for peace.</hi> And what if it will needs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and hide it ſelf? what is then to bee done? S. <hi>Peter</hi> wils vs in this caſe to <hi>follow peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.11</note> 
               <hi>&amp; inquire after it.</hi> And how if we knowe not where to finde it, or how to follow it? Then muſt wee take the Apoſtles counſell,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.11 <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Col 3.15.</note> and <hi>ſtudy for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Reaſon may be giuen (amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that might bee rendred) for this truth, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Apoſtle makes: <hi>You are called to it in one body.</hi> Where, the reaſon of it is double: firſt, from their vocation, They <hi>were called to it;</hi> and that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16595:34"/>
by men, who by their lawes require peace, but eſpecially by God: And that not onely in thoſe generall precepts of the word before quoted and the like, where this duty is vrged; but in ſpeciall maner in the word of reconciliation: That word that conuerts vs, which is called The <hi>Goſpell of peace,</hi> which makes lambs of lions, as the Prophet ſheweth when he ſpeaks of the fruits of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in the Kingdom of Chriſt. <hi>The wolf,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Iſay 11.6</note> 
               <hi>ſhall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard ſhall lie with the kid, and the calf and the lion, and the fat beast toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and a little childe ſhall binde them.</hi> The meaning is, that in the Kingdome of Chriſt the Goſpell ſhould make the moſt mighty, fierce and cruell, who were as lions and wolues, and ſuch like; to put off their woluiſh and lion-like nature, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gentle, milde and peaceable.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon that he giues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2</note> is from their mutuall relation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In one body.</hi> They were members of one body. And as it is vnnatural and vnſeemly, To ſee a man to rend and tear his owne fleſh: ſo is it moſt vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and vnſeemly for Chriſtians, To bite and deuour the one the other, by jarring, wrangling, or complaining.</p>
            <p>The enemies vnto peace are heer to bee repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: Such as thoſe of whom <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> Pſal. 120.5.6.7</note> 
               <hi>Wo is wee that I ſoiourn in Meſech, and dwel in the tents of Kedar. My ſoule hath long dwelt with him that hates peace. I am for peace: but, when I ſpeak, they are for warre.</hi> They are neuer well but when they are in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16595:35"/>
brabblings, contentions, and ſutes of law: if they be out of theſe, they are out of their own element; as a fiſh out of the water. You ſhall hear little elſe come from between their lips but <hi>Law, Law, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Iuſtice;</hi> and that for matters of no moment, for the value of a groat; nay leſs, for very nothing. And when there is difference between them and any other, how hardly are they drawne to peace, or any good agreement? A Bear is with far more eaſe drawne vnto the ſtake, than they to that. The like failings may be found in priuate families be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the husband and wife, parent and childe, maſter and ſeruant; to the diſhonour of God, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort of themſelues, and ruine of the whole houſe.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that there is ſo much complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the married eſtate: for, ſcarce more vſe it, than doo accuſe it. And how ſo? They them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues make bitter ſauce, and then cry out of the meat: they liue not in that eſtate according to Gods direction, but after their owne luſts; From <hi>whence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 4 1</note> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſheweth, <hi>proceed warres and contentions.</hi> The houſe is full of brawles and chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: diſcord driues the bleſſing out of doores. The Sonne of peace is not there:<note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.6</note> peace doth not reſt there. No wonder then if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note>To the practice of peace let vs be all exhorted. Would to God wee could once frame our ſelues to liue in it; and thoſe vnquiet ſpirits amongſt vs would once turne themſelues to more amiable
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16595:35"/>
courſes. But let all ſuch as looke for peace from the God of peace, take vp <hi>Dauids</hi> Motto in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of hart: <hi>I am for peace.</hi> Let vs long after peace,<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.7</note> and endeauour it; ſeek peace, and purſue it. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces follow vs: vertues ſlee from vs. As wee muſt runne apace from vice, leſt it ouertake vs: ſo wee muſt runne as faſt after peace and other vertues, that we may ouertake them. Doth thy aduerſary offer thee peace? Then peace followeth thee: ſee thou imbrace it. Doth he not offer it? Then doo thou knock at the gate of peace, deſire to ſpeak with it: In ſo doing thou ſhalt ſhew thy ſelf to be a childe of peace.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I be ſo baſe as to yeeld to him?<note place="margin">Ob.</note> he did the wrong, let him ſeek peace.</p>
            <p>Nay:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R ſ.</hi> Eph. 4.26.27</note> why ſhould'ſt thou be ſo baſe as to yield vnto the diuell? For, whoſoeuer giueth place to wrath, giueth place vnto the diuell. Hee offred the wrong, and yet ſeeketh not peace: it is his weaknes and folly. Doo thou ſeek an end, and purſue peace: it will bee thy wiſedome and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>There was ſometimes a variance betwixt two famous Philoſophers; <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> and <hi>Aeſchines. Aristippus</hi> comes to <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> and ſeeks for peace. <hi>Aeſchines</hi> gladly entertaineth ſuch a motion. Well, ſaieth <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> remember though I am your elder, yet I ſought the peace. True, ſaid <hi>Aeſchines;</hi> and for this I will euer acknowledge you to bee the worthier man. For, I began the ſtrife; but you the peace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16595:36"/>Hee that began the quarrell is the worſt; and he that procures Peace, the worthieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Motiues to peace</note>Sundrie are the reaſons or motiues which ſcripture vſeth to preſſe the endeuour of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It would be too long to number all: theſe are ſome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1</note>Firſt, our calling is in and vnto peace, as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted and now againe will touch:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>God is a God of peace; Chriſt is the Prince of peace;</hi> the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is <hi>the Goſpell of peace;</hi> the <hi>Godly</hi> are <hi>children of peace.</hi> Wee haue one Shepheard and are of one ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, liue in one Church which is the houſe of God, feed at one table; ſtrong bonds all to binde vs to the peace. How fowle a thing then is it to ſee diſcord amongſt ſuch as are knit together with ſo ſtrong a tye? The Creatures in the Ark (as we know) agreed together, though of a fierce cruell and deuouring nature. A great ſhame then will it bee to vs, that liue in the Arke of Gods Church, if wee agree not: It is for dogges and ſwine to barke and grunt one at another, and not for Sheepe and Lambes; all the world would wonder, to ſee them bite and teare their fellows. If then wee profeſſe our ſelues to be members of this Church, ſheepe of this fold whereof Chriſt is Shepheard, let vs liue in loue: for how can we, with any comfort, looke him in the face, when we ſo farre differ from the nature and properties of his ſheepe, in eating vp and deuouring of our brethren?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Motiue.</hi>
               </note>Againe, it is <hi>good and pleaſant,</hi> ſayth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16595:36"/>
               <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 132.1.</note> for <hi>brethren to dwell together in vnitie and peace.</hi> And no wonder,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar. cit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a cal. de vera pac.</note> for the very name of peace is beautifull and louely (ſayth an ancient) and therefore the practiſe of it muſt exceede. There are ſome things good which are not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, as <hi>Patience</hi> and tolerance of euils: Some things pleaſant but not good, as <hi>Epicuriſme</hi> and voluptuous liuing: Some things neither good nor pleaſant, as <hi>Malice, Enuie.</hi> But of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Concord</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) as wee ſee, it is both good and pleaſant: In it, and the practice of it, both theſe are met.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>where ſtrife is there is confuſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Motiue.</hi> Iames 3.16</note> 
               <hi>and euery euill worke,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> 1. <hi>Confuſion,</hi> For the breaking of Relatiues, is the ruine of Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues: we ſtand not of our ſelues, but vpon refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.<note place="margin">Liuius Decad. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> I haue read of a fitting ſtorie for this our purpoſe, and this it is. It ſometimes fell out that there was a great variance betweene the Nobles and Commons of Rome, inſomuch that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple banded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues together, to the great indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of the Common-wealth. The Senate ſent vnto the people, one <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Oratour, to perſwade them; and hee tells them this parable. On a time, the members of the body obiected againſt the ſtomake, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured all, and took no paines, but idly and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhly lay in the midſt of the body, while the reſt of the members laboured full ſore: Hereupon the eye would not ſee for it, nor the hand worke for it, nor the foot walke for it, nor the mouth
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16595:37"/>
aske for it, nor the teeth chew for it; but euerie member refuſed any more to doe it office. And what followed hereupon? The ſtomake wanting meate, and beeing empty, the eye began to bee dimme, the hand weake, the ſeet feeble; all the members beganne to be weake, and the whole body to wither: in ſo much that at laſt they were of neceſſity compelled to growe friends, and bee at agreement with it. By which parable he quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the people, and brought them to concord with the Senate. Thus, if the magiſtrates bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, people contentious, if one profeſſion or ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety quarrell with another, and deny mutuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their duties each to other; the whole body of that <hi>houſe, city, ſociety,</hi> muſt needs diſſolue. When the husband and the wife draw not euenly in the yoke: when one brings fire, and the other hath no water to quench it: when children are refractory; ſeruants waſters, and the like: there muſt needs be a decay of this family. Thus then wee ſee, Where <hi>ſtrife is, there is confuſion.</hi> And yet S. <hi>Iames</hi> goes further, and addeth, <hi>euery euill work:</hi> and that moſt truely. For, where ſtrife is, &amp; peace wanting, the Lord ſeeth, and men may euidently perceiue, that there are euil thoughts, euil words, and euill practices of all kindes. Where ſinne and ſatan bear ſway, it cannot otherwiſe be, but ſuch places muſt bee filled with all manner of polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Let the conſideration of theſe things ſo far preuail with vs, as that we may bee more in loue with this grace which is much ſet by of the Lord,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16595:37"/>
and auoid ſtrife which Gods abhorres.</p>
            <p>But how may a man become thus peaceable &amp; quiet?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> And what muſt be done for the attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this grace?</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> remoue all thoſe things which are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to peace: and they are either <hi>Inward</hi> or <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> Inward, as thy luſts; which is the fountain of all thy diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentments, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> verefieth.<note place="margin">Iames 4.1</note> Of which there are three principall. The one is <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 2.</note> of which S. <hi>Iames</hi> makes mention in the place before quoted: and this is a great enimy to peace, and a diſquieter of it. It was enuy which wrought that vnquietneſs between <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his brethren: for, <hi>the Patriarchs, moued with enuy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 37.4 Acts 7.9</note> 
               <hi>ſould</hi> Ioſeph <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Egypt.</hi> Enuy wrought all that vnquietneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Saul:</hi> for,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.8</note> when once <hi>Dauid</hi> was in credit aboue him, he had few quiet daies after. And what is it but Enuy, which breedeth moſt of our factions in ſocieties, oppoſition in ſectaries, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation in equals, and moleſtation to ſuperiors? And who ſees not, what a hand <hi>Enuy</hi> hath in moſt ſutes and debates, which are in our Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice daily pleaded? No maruell therefore Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 3.14 Rom. 13.13</note> elſewhere joyneth them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: for indeed they are ſeldome ſeparated. If thou would'ſt follow peace, withſtand that.</p>
            <p>A ſecond is <hi>Pride; by which,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13.10</note> 
               <hi>men make contention:</hi> and therefore theſe two alſo are well yoaked together as twinnes,<note place="margin">Phil 2.3</note> by our Apoſtle writing to the Philippians, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.3. This is that which maketh men now-adaies ſo proue to offer
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16595:38"/>
wrongs, and ſo vnwilling to put vp wrongs bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g offred. In all ages it hath been manifeſted, that where pride is deepeſt, there patience hath been ſhalloweſt: and they that ouerflow with the one, haue been void and empty of the other. And in another place <hi>Salomon</hi> hath this Prouerb;<note place="margin">Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> 
               <hi>Hee that is of a proud ſpirit ſtirreth vp ſtrife.</hi> By both which prouerbs we ſee clearly, that there is no greater inſtigator to vnquietnes, then pride and vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is. If therefore we would not vex our ſelues &amp; others with brawls and needleſſe contentions, let vs purge our hearts of this turbulent humour; which maketh men ſo ſtout in their conuerſation, contentious in prouocation, injurious in action, full of moleſtation, and far from pacification.</p>
            <p>A third luſt, which is an enemy to peace, is <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity</hi> or a <hi>buſie-meddling</hi> in things that concerne vs not: and therefore the Apoſtle joyneth theſe two likewiſe;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.11</note> 
               <hi>Study to be quiet, and do your owne bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</hi> And this was a main cauſe of that vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which was among the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">2 Theſ 3.11</note> which walked diſorderly (or vnquietly) working not at all, but were buſie-bodies: they loued to haue an oar in euery mans boat; as our ſawcy inter-med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlers doo, who loue to bee meddling where they haue little cauſe, and leſſe thanks. This was cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as the chief cauſe of the Emperour <hi>Antonius</hi> his troubleſome raign, That he was full of curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, prying into the eſtates and conditions of other men. And who ſeeth not, that buſie prying eyes haue troubleſome hands and vnquiet hearts?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:16595:38"/>Deſireſt thou peace? would'ſt thou practiſe quietnes? then beware of buſie curioſity. It was that which our Sauiour reproued in <hi>Peter,</hi> when he enquired of Chriſt what <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould do.<note place="margin">Iohn 21 21 22</note> 
               <hi>What is that to thee,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour? <hi>follow thou mee.</hi> If things be thus or thus order'd in Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth by the wiſdome of thy gouernours, what is that to thee? follow thou Chriſt by wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king conſcionably in thy owne calling. There are neceſſary duties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now in that, which require the imploiment of the whole man.<note place="margin">Tantumne abs re tua eſt tibi, aliena vt cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s?</note> There is work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at home: why doſt thou buſy thee abroad? Theſe, among many others, are ſome inward cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of vnquietnes and diſcontent, and enemies to peace. There are other <hi>outward Enemies</hi> to the practice of this grace; <hi>perſonall diſturbers</hi> of peace, who muſt bee ſhunned: as firſt, The <hi>tale-bearer,</hi> who buſieth himſelf in raiſing tales, and carrying newes to the defamation of others. Of theſe and concerning theſe, <hi>Salomon</hi> thus ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">Pro. 26.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Where no wood is, there the fire goeth out: ſo where there is no tale-bearer, the ſtrife ceaſeth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iam. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Such were thoſe of whom the Apoſtle complaineth: <hi>They being idle goe about from houſe to houſe, prattling and buſying themſelues with what is not conuenient.</hi> So long as theſe are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, peace cannot poſſibly be followed: and therefore abhorre <hi>tale-bearing</hi> and <hi>tale-receiuing,</hi> if thou would'ſt lead a quiet and peaceable life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thy neighbours (for, indeed there is no great difference between either of theſe:<note place="margin">Fern de conſid. l. <hi>2.</hi> in fine.</note> the one hath the diuell in his tongue; and the other in his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16595:39"/>
ear; as a Father wittily obſerueth). And when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe Peddlers come (for,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.16</note> that very phraſe is attributed to them in ſcripture) deſiring to vent their ware, ſharply reproue them: And, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro 25.13</note> 
               <hi>As the North-winde driues away raine; ſo let thy angry countenance, a backbiting tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the <hi>tale-bearer,</hi> ſo the <hi>flatterer</hi> is a great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to peace.<note place="margin">Pro. 29.5</note> 
               <hi>A man that flattereth his neighbour, ſpreadeth a net for his feet,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe-man. His baſe minde is well matched with a mercenary tongue, which is a willing ſlaue to any mans eare: he neuer regardeth how true, but how pleaſing; and, like the Chameleon, will turne himſelfe into any colour for a booty. Beware of him, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou art that loueſt peace. <hi>The wounds of a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are faithfull:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27.6</note> 
               <hi>but the kiſſes of an enemy are to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet amongſt many other that might be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, one more muſt not be forgotten: and that is the <hi>wrangling Lawyer;</hi> who maketh it the myſtery of his profeſſion to nouriſh contention; who, out of a couetous deſire of gain, encourageth men to contend, and goe to law with neighbours: yea, though their cauſe be neuer ſo bad, yet they will ſay with <hi>Abſalon</hi> to euery man,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>His cauſe is good and righteous.</hi> I ſpeak not againſt all, but againſt ſome, and they that are vnconſcionable: againſt whom I take vp that complaint of Sir <hi>Thomas Smith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Tho. Smith de rep. Ang.</note> Theſe buſie-heads and prating pettifoggers are permitted by the juſt judgement of God, like flies,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16595:39"/>
lice, and other vermine, to diſquiet them who would practiſe peace. And therefore hearken not to theſe, you that would liue peaceably: for, they are of <hi>Demetrius</hi> his reſolution; <hi>Sirs, you know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>that by this craft we get our gain.</hi> And thus we haue ſome cauſes both internall and externall of vnpeacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe: the remoueal whereof is the firſt means for peaceable and quiet liuing.</p>
            <p>A ſecond means is practicall;<note place="margin">Second mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> conſiſting in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> or vpright dealing with thoſe among whom we liue: And this is an excellent means for our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing peaceably. <hi>Dauid,</hi> praying for his ſonne <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that God would giue him his judgements, that he might judge the people with righteouſnes, and the poor with equity, addeth;<note place="margin">Pſal 72.3</note> 
               <hi>The mountaines ſhall bring peace vnto the people, and the little hils righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi> Which is by ſome thus allegorized: The magiſtrates, as the mountains, ſhall keep the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in peace: and the little hils, the inferiour ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſhall enjoy quietnes; and all by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. This was that which <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> did commend to his ſon vpon his death-bed. <hi>Wouldeſt thou liue quietly, my ſonne,</hi> ſaid hee, <hi>and haue others with thee and by thee to liue peaceably? Then carry thy ſelf vprightly, deal plainly, iudge truly, abstain from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, right the wronged, relieue the oppreſſed, ſuppreſſe the great, &amp;c.</hi> And this anſwer did <hi>Solon</hi> make to one who asked him, what it was that kept men moſt from troubles: Do, ſaith hee, to others, as thou would'ſt be done vnto: ſo thou ſhalt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet others, nor others trouble thee. From w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:16595:40"/>
ſaying, ſee thou receiue inſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Third means.</note>To theſe let <hi>Prayer</hi> be added, that thou mayſt haue wiſedome from aboue;<note place="margin">Iames 3.17</note> 
               <hi>which wiſedome</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) is <hi>peaceable.</hi> This is more effectuall to the practice of quietneſſe then all the reſt: and without this the other will be ineffectuall; and therefore ſee thou fail not in this. Pray feruently, and thou ſhalt be enabled to liue peaceaby: <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum est.</hi> And thus wee haue ſeen what is to bee done for the leading of a quiet and peaceable life amongſt our Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>But are wee to haue peace with all men, and in all matters? Are there not ſome enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt, idolaters and hereticks? are we to haue peace with them? And are there not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers again ſo contentious, as that they will not hear of peace?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reſp</note>The Apoſtle anſwereth, <hi>If it bee poſsible, as much as in you lieth, liue peaceably with all men.</hi> Firſt, <hi>If it be poſsible,</hi> that is, ſo far forth as may ſtand with your faith and good conſcience, and no further: for, vnder pretenſe of peace the truth may not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied. <hi>Follow peace and holineſſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Our peace then muſt be a holy peace, and not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy:<note place="margin">Melius eſt diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duem pictatis ortum cauſa, quam vttioſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ordia. Hier.</note> for, a godly diſſenſion is far better than it. When queſtion is of matters of religion, when by our ſilence the truth is like to bee betraied, God diſhonoured, and the ſaluation of our Brethren hindred; in theſe caſes peace cannot be retained.</p>
            <p>Hence Apoſtles and Apoſtolike men haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to contend by preaching and by writing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16595:40"/>
againſt errors and ſuperſtitions (as <hi>Paul</hi> with the <hi>Galatians; Auguſtine</hi> againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and ſo others) rather then by holding their peace to betray the truth of Chriſt. So ought wee then to haue peace with men, as that we doe not make warre with God. If the truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be violated, pluck vp thy heart, be valiant and fight the Lords battaile; and chuſe rather to loſe peace, then truth and Iuſtice. Our peace is a warfare againſt Satan and his complices.<note place="margin">Pax noſtra b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam. Tert. l. ad Mart.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>So much as lieth in vs.</hi> Som are ſo quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome and contentious, as do one what hee can to appeaſe and pleaſe them, they will haue no peace. Towards theſe wee ſhall do our dutyes, when we are peaceably diſpoſed, neither giuing nor haſtily taking any occaſion of diſſenſion. We are to deſire and ſeeke peace as much as lieth in vs, that there be no defect in vs, no neglect of our duty. And if then we cannot gaine peace with them, we ſhal bee ſure to get praiſe with God: and though heer peace fly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, yet in the end peace ſhall be our portion.</p>
            <p>To dreame then of an vnity with the Papiſts, of an vniformity with Schiſmatickes, is an idle phantaſie. For, ſo long as one is an enemy to truth, the other an enemie to Peace, both ſet on miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bined in faction, though differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in faith; wee may wiſh for it, but neuer haue it.</p>
            <p>But is it lawfull for a man to ſue another at the law, ſeeing that ſeems to be contrarie to peace?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is lawfull if ther bee iuſt cauſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Rom. 13.4</note> 
               <hi>for the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16595:41"/>
beareth not the ſword in vain.</hi> He beareth it to puniſh wrong-doers, and defend the right: which hee cannot doo, if hee haue no knowledge of it. And how ſhall he knowe, if there be no Plaintiff? And yet with theſe Caueats:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Caueats in ſuing at the Law.</note>Firſt, not for euery trifle or treſpaſſe; but in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of waight and importance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, not vntill thou haſt offred peace, and it be refuſed; and that not once, but often.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, not accounting him whom thou im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleadeſt as an enemy; hauing war onely with his vices, but peace with his perſon.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, proſecuting it with mildneſſe, not with extreamity. As, in ſuing of bonds, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering dammages, mercy muſt be ſhewed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that rule of the Apoſtle; <hi>Let your modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be knowne vnto all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.5</note> Which rules being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; As thou maiſt lawfully vſe phyſicke for the recouery of thy health: ſo maiſt thou vſe the Law for recouering of thy right.</p>
            <p>And thus we haue ſeen what the Apoſtle in this precept requireth, &amp; how to perform that which he requireth at our hands. What now remaineth? but that wee put theſe things in practice, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to <hi>keep the vnity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.3</note> Let vs not be <hi>vnpeaceable</hi> with the <hi>peaceable:</hi> that argueth <hi>a diueliſh minde;</hi> nor <hi>vnpeaceable</hi> with the <hi>vnpeaceable:</hi> which argueth <hi>a corrupt mind;</hi> nor yet content our ſelues in that we are <hi>peaceable</hi> with the <hi>peaceable,</hi> for that argues but a <hi>ciuill minde:</hi> but, if it be poſſible, and as much as in vs lieth, let
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16595:41"/>
vs bee <hi>peaceable</hi> with the <hi>vnpeaceable:</hi> which is that that onely argues a <hi>true Christian, and heroical mind.</hi> And ſo ſhould we make it good, that wee are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with true grace;<note place="margin">Eſay 11.6.7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 14.17</note> and are true ſubjects of that <hi>kingdome</hi> which is the <hi>kingdom</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> whoſe <hi>king</hi> is peace.</p>
            <p>Peace was that laſt &amp; rich jewell, which Chriſt (departing to his Father) left his Spouſe for a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy. <hi>Peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue vnto you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14.27</note> It is the laſt duty I ſhall exhort you vnto; <hi>Be peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, my Brethren.</hi> I haue read of two Noble Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians who were at mortall hatred; and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing met with by their King, called <hi>Archidamus,</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Minerua,</hi> hee requires them to put their matter to an indifferent Vmpire. They chuſe the King himſelf. He makes them ſwear to abide his order: which accordingly they doo. Now, ſaith the King, I order, that you ſhall not go out of this Temple vntill you be friends. And ſo they were reconciled (for, an oath taken in that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was vnlawfull to bee broken). My Brethren, we are the Temple of God, and now heer met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Temple of God; and haue this day, and now doo partake together of the holy things of God: And yet, as <hi>I hear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 6 7</note> 
               <hi>there is vtterly a fault a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you in this reſpect, in that there are contentions one amongst another, and going to law one with another,</hi> and that onely for ſuch things as ſauour but of ſpleen. Might I be Vmpire, the like order would I giue as that King did: you ſhould not depart out of this Temple till you were reconciled. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16595:42"/>
my Beloued, the diuell is the authour of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion. Hee it was that went about at the firſt to ſeuer man from God: and it is he that now labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to ſeuer man from man. <hi>Christ</hi> is our <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the <hi>Lord of peace.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is the <hi>Shulamite,</hi> the <hi>Lady of peace.</hi> If thou belongeſt to Chriſt, or to his Church, be peaceable. And ſo much be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the duties whereto they are exhorted: now a word or two of the Argument or Motiue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are enforced.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>And the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> God is heer called the God of loue and peace, becauſe hee is the authour, approuer, and rewarder of it. And heer by the way it is worth our noting, how that the Apoſtle, praying for peace, or exhorting to peace, ſets God before him, as hauing that in him for which he praies, and of which hee ſpeaks, giuing ſuch titles to him as beſt fits the preſents ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument;<note place="margin">Doct. We are to ſee in God th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fulnes of theſe graces we deſire of him.</note> and may teach vs, <hi>wheneuer wee come to God by praier, ſo to conſider of him as that wee may ſee in him thoſe things we deſire.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Romans to patience and conſolation, fals to praying for them, and ſets God before him as a God of patience and conſolation.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.5</note> 
               <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation grant you, &amp;c.</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> he cals him the God of hope. <hi>The God of hope fill you with all ioy, &amp;c.</hi> And in the very next chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, perſwading to peace, ſets God before his eies as <hi>a God of peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 16.20</note> And thus the Church, when they flew to praier when <hi>Peter</hi> was impriſoned, ſeeking courage and ſtrength from God, ſet God before
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16595:42"/>
them as a God of power. <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4.24</note> 
               <hi>thou art God who hast made heauen and earth, and the ſea, and all that in them is, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed this is a notable help to faith,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> when men come to ask of thoſe whom they knowe haue enough of that they ſeek: and asking it onely in ſuch a meaſure, as that it will not be any dammage for them they ſue vnto to vouchſafe and grant, they then are almoſt certainely perſwaded they ſhall ſpeed. So ſhall wee ſeek things the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely at the hands of God, when wee ſee the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thoſe things to be in him.</p>
            <p>It cauſeth vs alſo to ſeek more earneſtly and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently.<note place="margin">Second reaſon.</note> The ſight of the Traueller's owne home makes him the more affectionately to long after it: ſo the true ſight of mercy and grace in God, will cauſe vs the more longingly to deſire it.</p>
            <p>Comeſt thou to God by praier for any grace?<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> Then ſee thou ſeeſt in him the fulnes of that grace thou praieſt for. Deſireſt thou mercy in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgiueneſſe of thy ſins? Conſider then of God as a God with whom there is <hi>plenty of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> Haſt thou fallen into relapſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſin again, a ſecond time? Conſider of God as a God that <hi>reſerueth mercy in ſtore</hi> for all ſuch as fall, though they fall often. Deſireſt thou the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of any promiſe that God hath made to the Church in generall, or thy ſelf in particular? Conſider then of God as a God of <hi>truth,</hi> as hee is <hi>Iehoua, yeſterday, to day, and the ſame alſo for euer.</hi> Art thou in any grief or miſery in body or in minde,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16595:43"/>
and deſireſt eaſe? Remember God as hee is a <hi>God of mercy and conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo for any other bleſſing thou wanteſt and deſireſt for thy ſelfe or others, with the ey of faith ſee it to bee in him when thou prayeſt to him. So thou ſhalt finde a ſtrong proppe for faith, and help to kindle thy affection: which happely thou thoughteſt not of as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. This from the Apoſtles practice: now more particularly to the words. Sundry might bee the collections from hence drawne: but I wil content my ſelfe with this one.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct. God is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of true loue and peace. <hi>Gal. 5.22</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Loue and peace are from God effectually, howeuer they may be obtayned and wrought by meanes inſtrumentally,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fruit of the ſpirit is Loue, Ioy, peace &amp;c.</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle. So then it is the ſpirit of God that works this in vs. And how often doth the Apoſtle in his epiſtles vſe this prayer! <hi>Grace and peace from God our Father, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee ſhewes vs who is the author of it, and from whom it comes. God giues it, in, through, and for the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Iames 1.17</note>And no wonder: for if <hi>Euerie good and perfect gift is from aboue, and commeth downe from the Father of lights,</hi> as Saint Iames ſpeaketh; then theſe likewiſe as well as other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>Want we theſe gifts and graces? ſee then where wee are to ſeeke them; euen from God aboue: and though we are to vſe the means yet let vs not reſt in the vſing of the meanes, but ſee we pray to God to bleſſe the meanes vnto vs. The Scripture is the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16595:43"/>
ordinarie meanes whereby theſe and other graces are wrought in vs inſtrumentally: yet it is God that muſt make his word efficacious and powerful for this end. <hi>Paul plants, Apollo waters;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 3 6</note> 
               <hi>God alone muſt giue the encreaſe. Rebecca</hi> may cooke the veniſon: but <hi>Iſack</hi> muſt giue the bleſſing. All that wee can doe is but to ſpeake vnto the eare: God is he that muſt ſpeak vnto the conſcience. I can call vpon you to <hi>bee perfect, to bee of good comfort, to bee of one mind, to liue in peace:</hi> but this God of peace muſt graunt it and giue grace to do it. <hi>Paul</hi> preacheth to <hi>Lydiaes</hi> eare: but God hath the key of her heart to open or keepe ſhut at his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Let vs ſo many then as would be perfect and thus liue in peace, ſue vnto this God of peace for theſe and all other graces, that wee may haue not onely <hi>Peace Externall</hi> with thoſe amongſt whome wee liue; but alſo <hi>Internall</hi> Peace of conſcience (which what it is none knoweth but thoſe who haue it) and ſo heereafter that ſame Peace <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> which eye hath not ſeen, eare hath not heard, neither is it poſſible the heart of man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. <hi>Now this God of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.21</note> 
               <hi>that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus, the great ſhepheard of the ſheep, through the bloud of the euerlaſting couenant, make vs perfect in theſe and all other good workes to doe his will, working in vs that which is pleaſant in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hom bee praiſe for euer and euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
